<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A perseruatiue, or triacle, agaynst the poyson of Pelagius lately renued, ... by the furious secte of the Annabaptistes ... By Willyam Turner, Doctor of Physick.</title>
            <author>Turner, William, d. 1568.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1551</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 104 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24368</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101787</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837590</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837590</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1922</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14060)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1922)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1012:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A perseruatiue, or triacle, agaynst the poyson of Pelagius lately renued, ... by the furious secte of the Annabaptistes ... By Willyam Turner, Doctor of Physick.</title>
                  <author>Turner, William, d. 1568.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[104] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By S. Mierdman] for Androw Hester,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>dwellyng in Powles churchyarde, at the wytt horsse next to Powles scole. An. 1551. The 30 of Ianuarij.]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-N.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes paragraphs from an attack on Turner by an unnamed Anabaptist, alternating with the former's answers.--NUC Pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Some pages marked and stained; title page mutilated with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anabaptists --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1922:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1922:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, or triacle, agaynſt the poyſon of Pelagius, lately renued, &amp; ſtyrred vp agayn, by the furious ſecte of the Annabaptiſtes: deuyſed by Wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyam Turner, Doctor of Phyſick.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Beleue not euery ſpirite, but proue the ſpirites, whether they be of God, or no.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1922:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1922:2"/>
            <head>To the moſte ſtedfaſt, godly, &amp; true prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of Gods worde, maiſter Hughe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timer: Wylliam Turner Phyſicion, wyſſheth long lyfe, and good helth: if it be the wyll, and pleaſure of almighty God: with continuaunce in al vertues, and godlynes: and Chriſt our ryghteouſnes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſame thing chaunceth nowe, and hath chaunced euer ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynning, vnto all true pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and defenders of Goddes holy worde: that chaunced vnto the noble, and doughtye warryer, Hercules. Hercules for the loue that he bare vnto his country toke many a ieoperdous, and labor ſum worke in hande: and euer after that one was ended, another began, ſo that they myght haue ſemed to be tyed together wyth chaynes: one dyd alwayes ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually, and almoſte touchingly folowe onother. But his trouble and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines, that he had with the kylling of the ſeuen hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded water ſnake called Hydra: is moſte lyke in all poyntes, vnto the labour ſum worke of Chriſtes ſoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diers, and true preachers, for euer as he kylled one heade with his arrowes, and ſtrooke it of with hys ſworde: There roſe vp another agayne, vntyll that at the length he deſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> them wyth fyrebran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Euen ſo the Apoſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſte, as they had ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med one labour, they were cumbred ſtreigth way with another. Fyrſt they had much a do, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertyng the Iewes from theyr euil lyfe: and not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le to do, to pull them from the falſe beleue that they
<pb facs="tcp:1922:3"/> had, to be iuſtified by the workes of the law: which<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for all that they kept not they had muche to do, to bryng the Iewes from the ceremonyes of Moyſes lawe: and to make them beleue, that they were put downe by the death of Chriſte. The turning of the heathen from ydolatry vnto the belefe in Chriſt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that they had conuerted many of the Iewes, was both a ieoperdous, and a tumbrous labour. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all theſe great laboures, there roſe vp a ſort of he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>retikes: who wold haue not only defaced, &amp; blotted out all of the prayſe, that the Apoſtels wan by theyr labours: but vtterly haue deſtroyed, and vndone all their doynges. The names of the heretikes were, Simon Magus, Ebion, and Corinthus. Auſten, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, and Hierom, with other lyke fathers, in their tymes, had great trouble and beeſines with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable enemies of Chriſtes trueth. And we in our tyme are not in all pointes vnlike vnto Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. For one labour euer ſucceſſiuely receyueth, and foloweth another. Firſt in Cambridge about .xx. yea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res ago, ye toke great paynes to put men from their wyl workes: as pylgrimage, and ſettyng vp of can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels: and with great labour ye brought many from them vnto the workes, that God commaunded ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſedly in his holy ſcripture: and to the reading, &amp; ſtudy of Gods worde: al dreames, and vnprofitable gloſes of men ſet a ſyde, and vtterly deſpiſed. Then this fundacion of Goddes worde, ones layde, we that were your diſciples, hadde much to do in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge: after your departing from vs: with them that defended praying vnto ſayntes, iuſtification of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, holye water, ſuperfluous holy dayes, the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the maſſe, lyinge of parſons fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, prouiſion for purgatorye, the ſyngle lyuyng of miniſters, and the ſuperſtitious choyſe of meates: &amp; many ſuche other doctrines, contrary vnto the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And though this ſtryfe agaynſt Gods enemies, were common to me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> many: yet I had ſpecially to do with a bucke: wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> a certayn man, that had a name of the colour of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>adder: with the fox and hys foſter: and with a certayn wytche, called mayſtres miſſa. But after I was eaſid from al theſe monſters, by the help principally of almyghty God, and by the
<pb facs="tcp:1922:3"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yde of the kyng, and his counſell: I thought to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue bene at good reſt, and quietnes from contentious ſtriuinges, wherewith I had bene muche troubled in tymes paſt: and had fully purpoſed, to haue ſet all my ordinaunce againſt groſſe vyces, and noughtye lyuyng of the people in this realme. But beholde ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſterte oute a woode ſpirite, muche perillouſer then all the beaſtes, that I had to do with before: not becauſe he is ſtronger, then the other: but becauſe his poyſon, that he intenderh to ſpoute oute, is more perillous, then the others poyſon was. Some man peraduenture wyll ſaye, that if I woulde, I myght haue auoyded all theſe perilles: if I would haue medled with my Phyſick only, &amp; not haue cumbred my ſelf with matters of diuinite: and that I am ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore well worthy this trouble. To whom I aunſwer, that if that I had had ſuch a conſcience, as to many now a dayes haue: that I could haue founde in my harte, to take the dignities, rewards, and lyuynges of Chriſtes churche, and to do nothyng for them, and if that I hadde not thought it better, that one man ſhould runne into ieopardy, then that many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes ſhould haue ben poyſoned with the poyſon of Pelagius: I myght in deede haue eaſely auoyded this perillous labour. But after that my lorde Arche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byſhop of Yorke, had ones geuen me a prebende: I could not be quiet, vntill that I had licence to reade, or preache. Whiche obteyned: I began to rede, and ſo to diſcharge mi conſcience. And becauſe I dyd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue, that diuerſe began to be infected with the poy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon of Pellagius: I deuiſed a lecture in Thiſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth, agaynſt two of the opinions of Pelagius: na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mely againſt that childer haue no original ſin, &amp; that they oughte not to be baptiſed. But within a few we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes after: one of Pelagius diſciples, in the defence of his maſters doctrine, wrote againſt my lecture, with all the cunnyng and learning, that he had. But leſt he ſhould glorye and crake amonge his diſciples, that I could not aunſwer him: and to the intent, that the venemous ſeede of his ſoweyng maye be deſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed, and ſo hyndered from bryngyng forth frute: I haue ſet out this boke, to aunſwer hym, in the one of his opinions: and (God wyllyng) when I haue ſet
<pb facs="tcp:1922:4"/> out my Herbal, I ſhal aunſuer hym to the other. And this ſmall worke I dedicate vnto you, as a worthy patrone for it. I myght haue dedicated it vnto ſome great man of aucthoritie, power, and ryches, but con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyderyng that nether aucthoritie, power, nor ryches, are able to defende my boke, if the Pelagians ſhould write agaynſt it: I haue choſen you as a patron, to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fende it with your learning: whiche is only a better defence, then all the dignitie &amp; riches of the worlde be they neuer ſo great. Nowe after that I haue deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you to be a patrone vnto my boke: I muſt aſke you counſel: how that I, and my felowes ſhal behaue our ſelues agaynſt this monſtere of our tymes: that ye may by our labours, be put afterwards to leſſe payne. This monſtre is in many poyntes lyke vnto the waterſnake with ſeuen heades. For as out of one bodye roſe ſeuen heades: So out of Pelagius roſe vp theſe ſeuen ſectes: Anabaptiſtes, Adamites, Loyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtes, Libertines, Swengfeldianes, Dauidianes, and the ſpoylers. Sum would thincke: that it were the beſt way, to vſe theſame weapones agaynſt thys manyfolde monſtre, that the papiſtes vſed agaynſt vs: that is material fyre, and faggot. But me thynk: ſeyng it is no materiall thynge, that we muſt fyght withal, but goſtly, that is a woode ſpirite: that it we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re moſte mete, that we ſhould fyght with the ſwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of goddes word, and with a ſpirituall fyre againſt it: or elles we are lyke to profit but a litle in our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynes. Paule, a noble capitayn of Chriſtes warres, in hys epiſtle, that he wrote vnto the Epheſianes: counſelleth his yonge ſcholars (whiche, he ſayth, muſt fyght againſt ſpirituall craftines and ſubtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) to put vpon them all the hole armour of God, &amp; to take the ſpirituall ſworde, the worde of God. Chriſte alſo in the .iiij. of Mathew teacheth vs by his example to fygh, with ſpirites, with the ſpirituall wepones of the worde of God, as he dyd: and ſo dyd Auſten, and Hierom, coniure, and dryue away ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in theyr dayes. Then when as the enemie is a ſpirite, that is, the goſte of pelagius, that olde here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike: ones welle laid, but now of late to the great ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perdie of many rayſed vp agayn: the wepones, &amp; the warriers, that muſt kyll thys enemie, muſt be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall.
<pb facs="tcp:1922:4"/> As for ſpiritual weapons, we may haue enow out of the ſtore houſe, or armory of the ſcripture: to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>found &amp; ouertrow all the goſtly enemies be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo many But where, &amp; from whence, ſhal we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſpiritual warriers ynow fit for this fyght? If that we had no mo enamies, but this alone, the fewer ſol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diers would ſerue: but when as tie ſpite of fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and aduoutre, the rauening rentrayſyng ſprite, the ſprite of gluttony, the ſprete, of Lucian, Iuliane, and Epicure, within finite ſwarmes mo of ſpiritual ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, haue beſegd the churche round about: we had nede of a great dele of mo ſouldiers, then al the ſcoles that are in this realme are able to ſet furth: if ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſcoles haue bene put down of late, as the comon rumor reporteth. But what wold that help to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of warriers: if that the olde numbre of ſcoles were ſet vp again: if ether the ſcolars ſhuld want li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings to fynd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vntill they myght come to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyt ſouldyers: or if they grewe vp, &amp; became good ſoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diers: then the lyuing, that was ones apointed only for ſpiritual ſouldiers: ſhuld be giuen ether vnto car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal wariers, or to other that by their dignite haue forſworne all common ſpiritual war, and myght get their liuyng wel enough otherwyſe by their owne vocations? For that wold both diſcorage ſcolares fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this kinde of ſtudy: and wold compel them, that were able to exercyſe the ſpiritual war, to turne them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to other ſciences, to get their liuinges therwith. For although the war be ſpiritual, and the ſouldiers occupie chiefly their ſprites<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet are they not without bodies: which (as they are worthy) muſt nedes haue meat, drinck, &amp; cloth, &amp; all other neceſſaries. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if that we will haue the church of Chriſt, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the enemies, wherwith it is nowe beſieged: we muſt prouide not only liuings for yonge ſcolars, that they may continue in this godly ſtudy: but alſo that the rype, &amp; perfit ſouldiers may haue ſufficient li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uinges: that they nede not for lack of liuinges, to ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to their aduerſaries, for better wages, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit tre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon againſt vs. Almighty God preſerue you: &amp; graunt you ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, &amp; helth: that ye may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in preachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, to the ouertrowing of al wickednes, &amp; to the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the true worde of God: to whom be al honour and glory, for euer and euer Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb facs="tcp:1922:5"/>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
               <head>D. HVGONI LATIMERO NI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colaus Grimoaldus. S.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Optime non pigra florens Latimere ſenecta:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rex, que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regis prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſapienſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Senatus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tempore que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>go cupit haec reſpublica ſaluu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eccè tui ſimilis ueteranus hic, alter &amp; ipſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ad debellandos in religione rebelles</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Millibus è multis te gaudet habere patronum.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quàm benè ſpectatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpectatus, amicus amicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aduocat: ut fractis pariter ſuccurrere rebus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Poſsitis, domini quas impetit hoſtis acerbus?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſtiadas Chriſti ſic ſic defendere partes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cónuenit et iunctis huc huc co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>currere turmis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> utinam pugnatorum ſic copia creſcat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Creſcit ut hoſtilis numerus. Sed ꝙd querar? aut quos</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Incuſem? O mores tetros, ô te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pora dira.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sunt fuci, pecus ignauum: qui melle fouentes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Corpora, deſertis ſtationibus, omnia produnt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sunt ceſsatores: quos tu, Latimere, notâſti</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Saepè (Deus faxit, fuerit ne fabula ſurdis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dicta) ſuas qui cùm res curent, &amp; ſibi uiuant:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cùm pulchros titulos, &amp; nomen inane bonoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bellatorum habeant: uberrima praemia capta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Debita militibus nauis, ſtrenuae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cateruae.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Armatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loca, ſed no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> arma capeſſunt:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Immò aciem turbant longè turpiſsima monſtra.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ingruit ampla manus, uis multò maxima ſaeuit.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:1922:5"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>En inimica cohors: en Papa, Pelagius adſunt:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cinctus adeſt crebro, ſceleru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> caput, agmine Daemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facilè inuada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, uinca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, rega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ex qua parte iacent torpentia me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra ueterno?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quid facimus? quae tanta uiros ignauia perdit?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arua, facos, pecudes, uillas, armaria, tecta,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diuitias, et opes fragiles, peritura<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> regna,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quantis praeſidijs ultrò defendimus omnes?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (heu me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſtupidas, heu mortua corda)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eripitur coelu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nobis ſtertentibus ipſum.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ve miſerae genti: populum quae ſata Britannu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vrgent, cuſtodes ubi ſunt uulpeſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, lupi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nunquàm herclè, nun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>quam</ex>
                     </expan> uictoria clara redibit:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ni ſomno addictos homines, &amp; tempore belli</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Castra relinquentes: faciant uel prorſus abire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cedentes alijs, proprium uel munus obire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui res humanas aequa ditione gubernant.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> colant ſummis ſtudijs, &amp; honoribus illos:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui rectis imbuti animis, &amp; robore magno,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lubrica conſtanti ſuperant mendacia uero:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hic uti Turnerus fecit, fortiſsimus heros.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
               <head>Ad <hi>D.</hi> Guilielmum Turnerum.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Perge, faue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te Deo (Turnere grauiſsime) perge</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Exornare libris tempora noſtra tuis:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et ui coeleſti portenta nefanda domare,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quae populu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peſte noce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te premunt:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gaude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t uentres pingues, magni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> magiſtri</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:1922:6"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cum uafra obſcuris arte latere locis:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>preſsiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t manibus, gregibuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> relictis:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nouis nummis arca tumeſcit hians.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Praedentur uigiles, conceſſo tempore fures.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sed quis erit finis? quis, rogo, finis erit?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Intoleranda dabit uindex tormenta ſupremus:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et ſcelera horrebit talia quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pius.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tu uero inſtos reprimens acerrimus hoſtes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Defendenſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tui uerba colenda Dei:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Captabis nitido laetiſsima munera coelo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Munera per nullos interitura dies.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Perg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> igitur Papas animo contemnere toto,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Clarûm exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pla uirûm clara tene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da memor:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neu quoſuis facilè Chriſti patiaris in aede</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quelibet ignaros dogmata praua ſequi.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Immortale tibi fauet iſto nomine numen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pro<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuo genitor pignore ſummus habet.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et ſolidas grates imo de pectore promunt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lucis amatores, candida turba tibi.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eſt ſatius placuiſſe Deo, dum recta tueris:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quàm ſeruire ſtylo diſsimulante, malis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eſt ſatius, paucis iuſtis tua ſcripta probari,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quàm cum mille hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laude ſilere leui.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ergò, faue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te Deo (Turnere grauiſsime) perge</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Illuſtrare libris tempora noſtra tuis.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
               <head>Ad Catabaptiſtam.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Amice, ſi ſapis, tibi caue: caue,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:1922:6"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bonum ne nomen amittas apud bonos:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Item ne corpus in periculum trahas:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neu mentes plurimas perdens, perdas tuam.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Duas res, obſecro, quantum potes, fuge.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eſt una magna peſtis, Ignoratio,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quae ueritatis lucen neſcit aſſequi.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eſt altera, praeter hanc, lues uel maxima,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Doceri uelle ſe negans Superbia.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Autore me: qui non minùs ſanè tibi</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rectè conſultum, <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>quam</ex>
                     </expan> mihi uolo, &amp; meis:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sacrum pia uocabis uoce Spiritum:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui pectori tuo talem modeſtiam</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Inſtillet, ut ſibi planè renunciet:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Veri<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> noſcendi te amore ſedulo</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Inſpiret, abiectis malis affectibus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ad hunc modum, ſi comparare te uoles:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tunc, tunc, uolume<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hoc cùm corde légeris</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Attento, candido, benigno, ſerio:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E doctus, optimam redibis in uiam.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To the reder.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lyke as in tyme of Goddes reuengyng wrath:</l>
                  <l>When fyry Mars, when Saturn colde and drye</l>
                  <l>Wyth Soonne in Scorpion conſpyrid hathe,</l>
                  <l>And from the ſouth vnholſoome breath is do flye:</l>
                  <l>Venoomde vapors, they poyſon by and bye</l>
                  <l>The duſkid ayer infectid is the water:</l>
                  <l>Corrupt is foode of mennis ſubſtance the matter:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The moyſture hore then rottith inwardly:</l>
                  <l>Then ſtoppid ar the holes of outerſkyn:</l>
                  <l>Then from the hart the heate to veynes dooth hye:</l>
                  <l>Then natiue vice abatith all within,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1922:7"/>
                  <l>Drawne faſt together, dryed, and dryuen full thyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then waſtith lyuyng wyghtis, without defence,</l>
                  <l>The ragyng plage, and cruell peſtilence:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ryght ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Deuyll out ſent to trouble vs,</l>
                  <l>With hellyſh hotlynges, with Saturnians,</l>
                  <l>With creepyng beaſtes, the light defaſyng thus,</l>
                  <l>As in this ſtorme ſtyll ſtoute Pelagians</l>
                  <l>Blowes forth the blaſtes of Antichriſtians:</l>
                  <l>The bondeſſaues of Satan, ſowers of lyes,</l>
                  <l>Maſters of myſchief, trompes of hereſyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now foſtrid is a maddyng maladye</l>
                  <l>In heddis neewfanglid, and beewitched thaughtis:</l>
                  <l>Refuſyng all goode leachis remedye:</l>
                  <l>Goddis trouth to fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſies plucking, that be naughtis:</l>
                  <l>Lewde people drawyng by vnſkylfull draughtis:</l>
                  <l>Vntyll the ſymple ſoules, without redres,</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſt of error fayntyth ſuccourles.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet, lo, whan as that murren is ſo brymme:</l>
                  <l>To his, God ſhapith ſoouerayne ſauegarde:</l>
                  <l>By chaunge of place: by purgyng euery lymme:</l>
                  <l>By bytter ſowle, by thynne diet, and harde:</l>
                  <l>By mouyng members toward, and frowarde:</l>
                  <l>By Vipars bodye bet, with herbis not voyde</l>
                  <l>Of vertue: if her hedde, and tayle be ſtroyde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Likewiſe goode helpis God giues againſt the ſore</l>
                  <l>Diſeaſe of mynde, and brayne fantaſticall:</l>
                  <l>To ſeewe ſage companye, to vſe nomore</l>
                  <l>Vnholſome ſtedis: to clenge, and to let fall</l>
                  <l>The Proude, and coye conceyte: withdrawyng all</l>
                  <l>Fat fare,, and fyne, ſtraunge diſſhes to forſake:</l>
                  <l>For Alexander, Woolfbane leſt thou take:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To practiſe heuenly lore, and wyſdome brought</l>
                  <l>Downe from aboue: this medicine to applye</l>
                  <l>To reſcue folke, that hath contagion cought,</l>
                  <l>And eeke to ſaue a man continuallye</l>
                  <l>From dedly poyſen: yea or els to trye,</l>
                  <l>Which way thou mayeſt cut of the adders hedde,</l>
                  <l>Or eaſe thy frende vnto thy ancorfledde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wylt thou be ſounde? wylt thou be ſafe, &amp; ſure?</l>
                  <l>Folowe, folowe thys worke, thou haſte in hande.</l>
                  <l>Wylt thou hym kenne, that cauſe is of cure?</l>
                  <l>He that abrode here, and out of the lande,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1922:7"/>
                  <l>He that in warde, did Antichriſte witſtande:</l>
                  <l>Goode Doctor Turner: who by ſkyll is able</l>
                  <l>To proue the ſoothe, and to confounde eche fable.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Thomas Norton to the reder.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Wee may wyte, if wee wyll, by holy writ</l>
                  <l>The lore of the lorde, that ledeth to lyfe:</l>
                  <l>Wee may ſee, if wee ſeche, and fynde in it</l>
                  <l>The fall of falſhed, the ſteuching of ſtrife:</l>
                  <l>The tryall of trewth: the guide of our gate:</l>
                  <l>Calbemeſſe of hart: what to loue, or to hate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yea and ſo may wee ſee, that it alone</l>
                  <l>Should be ſought, to finde that wee ought to ſeche:</l>
                  <l>No mynde of man to bee buylded on:</l>
                  <l>No counſell, no cuſtome can bee our leche,</l>
                  <l>To purge the poyſon: gyue ſalue for the ſore:</l>
                  <l>Or hathe helth for the harmed hart in ſtore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They more the miſchief: they prolong the payne:</l>
                  <l>Ad more force to the fier, for the want</l>
                  <l>Of water of the word: and worke in vayne</l>
                  <l>Let vs hye to hym: whoes ſkill is not ſcant.</l>
                  <l>Whoes will dothe not, to better our bale:</l>
                  <l>To leſſe our loſſe. Yea to quit vs of all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A peſtilent plage, a poyſonons ill</l>
                  <l>Hath ſowen ſores in certaigne now of late:</l>
                  <l>A wood ſprited hart: with a wayward wyll:</l>
                  <l>A ſtubborne ſtomache, to nouriſhe debate:</l>
                  <l>Blered, yea blynded eyes: a braſen breſt:</l>
                  <l>A leden brayne: I recken not the reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Agaynſt theſe euell ayres thou mayſt haue here</l>
                  <l>(Take it, and taſte it, yea let none be left)</l>
                  <l>A tryed triacle, to kepe the clere.</l>
                  <l>Lechecraft not only reſtoreth the reſt,</l>
                  <l>But alſo preſerueth vnharmed helth.</l>
                  <l>This phyſike is free and eſy God welth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And euen as lerned leches do oftentymes</l>
                  <l>(Triall techeth dayly to fore our eyes)</l>
                  <l>Put in poyſon, to make for medicines:</l>
                  <l>So make their bale thy boote: their loſſe lykewyſe</l>
                  <l>Thy gaine, to warne the how thou ought to wyrche</l>
                  <l>To glory of God, and help of the Churche.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A watcherime to the magiſtrates, for the</l>
                  <l>Catabaptiſtes, and their patriarches.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:1922:8"/>
               <lg type="acrostic">
                  <l>
                     <hi>C</hi>ommune tryall techeth them, that be wyſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O</hi>ff thynges forepaſt to fynde, what will befall,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>W</hi>ee haue ſeen, herof what end dothe aryſe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>C</hi>Confounding of kyngdomes, decay of all.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>H</hi>eede taken to warning ſaueth from fall.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui uoudra bien du treſſainct lauement</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>De Christ Sauueur la uerité ſcauoir,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ce liuret liſe, ou tout entierement</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Turner l'eſcrit d'un haut stile &amp; ſcauoir</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Au contrainct &amp; meu pour ne vouloir</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Du faux Satan ne des ſiens le poiſon</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Estre espandu en ſaincte maiſon</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Que Ieſus Christ de ſon ſang alauée</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Leſquelz auoient ſans aucune raiſon</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Encontre luy leur grand corne leuée.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
               <head>Thomas Nortonus Sharpenhauius Lectori.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quando ſic ſummo pariter parenti</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Constat &amp; rerum domino placere,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cuius in cunctis manet una ſemper</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>firma uoluntas:</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vt uel exipſis etiant malorum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Improbe factis ſua proferatur</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Laus, quod ruentus moderetur at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>tempora ſolus:</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Commodum lector ſimul ó beate</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In tuum cedant, animoſa quiſquis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In tui cauſa ducis exhibebis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>pectora Chriſti:</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:1922:8"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In tuum proles igitur Satanae</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quicquid hic Chriſtum uomuit ueneni,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Robur integro, medicamen aegro</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>en tibi factum.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Is quod errauit, moneat ſupernae</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Candido grates animo ferendas</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gratiae, quate ſibi chariorem</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>praetulit illi.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inſuper quae ſint, doceat cauenda.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fauſta Turnero medico precare</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tam pio: mentem quoque ſaniorem</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>haereſiarchae.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
               <head>Randolphus Hurleſtonus ad Lectorem.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Praecipit nobis, nihil ut patretur</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Proſus iniuſté: ſua ſet relinqui</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Omni bus mandat deus ille ſumo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>ſummus olympo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nonne ius ductum uiolat nefande</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eripi qui uult puero tenello,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dum nequit primos propriam per annos</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>dicere cauſam,</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Illud aeterni ſolidum ſigillum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faederis, per quod ſumus infauore:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Per quod &amp; nobis rata cuncta fiunt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>munera Chriſtis</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nuperat quidam ſtygijs abundis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Proruens, parumſpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iare pubem</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1922:9"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nititur tanto precio, malignus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>inuidus hoſtis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quem graui pugna ſtrenué retundit</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ille Turnerus, decus at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> lumen</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Angliae: cuius fuit in Papistas</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>inclyta palma.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Conſulas doctos igitur labores</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In bonam partem, tibi qui dicantur:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>At<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> perpendas animo tenaci</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>quae liber offert.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1922:9"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Est Deus uerax, omnis homo mendax.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S allmighty god is the auctor of al truth, yea euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth it ſelfe, as Chriſte, in theſe wordes doth teſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fy: I am the waye, the truth, &amp; the life: ſo all lyinge, &amp; falſhod co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth from the deuyll: as Chriſt ſayth in Iohn: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll is a lyer, &amp; the father of the ſame. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is not hard to knowe, of what ſpirit ye be: whych begyn your boke with ſo many vnſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mefaced lyes, and goo forward with falſehod: &amp; both in reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of other mens doynges, &amp; ſayinges, and alſo in matters of religion: do willingly, and adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly, treade doune the truth: mainteyning the doctryne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll (I meane hereſy, &amp; falſe
<pb facs="tcp:1922:10"/> doctrine) with lies, falſhod, and ſomtime with ſubtil Sophiſtry: which I reken the deuill at cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain times powreth into you, to defende hys doctryne wyth all, for al the learned men that haue diſputed with you in your opini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, whit whom I haue ſpoken, iudge you to be ſo iklender a clerk: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they think y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye neuer ler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned nether ſophiſtry, nor logike nether anye good ſcyence in all your life, ſauinge only muſyke: wherin yf I be ſo cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning, as the como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> report maketh you: it had ben better for you to haue ſonge your part agaynſte me in tune: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue to vnlearnedly, and lyingly written againſt me, out of ordre, and oute of tune, from the truth. firſt, as hereafter folo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth, thus do ye begyn.
<q>☞ Maſter Turner intendynge to proue
<pb facs="tcp:1922:10"/> that infantes maye well and oughte to be baptyſed in theyr infancye, by the worde of God, began fyrſte, as I am enformed, to commend vnto hys audience the cuſtom of colleges, and ſcoles in Oxforth, and cambrydge, and ſuche other: where it is or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deyned, that ſuche as ſhall be admytted to the feloweſhyppe of ſuche houſes, ſhall heare the ſtatutes where vnto they ſhal be bounde .iiij. tymes in the yeare, that they may knowe theyr charge therby, and kepe it: Whiche cuſtome is in dede a reſonable and landable cuſtom, but not in all poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes agreable to his purpoſe. For there they receyue no infantes to the felowſhyppe of theyr houſes: but ſuch as are growen to vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtanding, and do erneſtly ſewe to be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiued: and being receiued, haue theyr year of probation, to ſe whyther they can alow, and lyke the company wyth all theyr ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and condytyons, and the companye them or not, or euer they be admytted.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ In the fyrſt ſentence of your boke, ye teach the readers of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (to make them like you) a loud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly: that is to wyt: that I dyd
<pb facs="tcp:1922:11"/> alledge the cuſtome of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ſtatutes of colleges, iiij. tymes in the yeare, to the fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowes of the colleges: to proue, that chyldren in their infancy both ought, and myght well be baptyſed. which is playne falſe. For al though I intended in the end of my ſermond to proue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> infantes myght wel be baptiſed in their infancy: yit in the begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning of my ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, I cited and alledged not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner of reding of ſtatutes in colleges, to proue that infantes ſhuld be baptiſed: but to teache my hearers, that were preſent in the church: that I thought it as neceſſarye for Chriſten men, to haue their bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme to be oft opened, and decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red vnto them: wherein is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in a ſmall roume, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole
<pb facs="tcp:1922:11"/> ſumme of a Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mannes pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion: as it was neceſſarye for ſcolers to haue theyr ſtatutes red .iiij. tymes in the yeare. For I had bene worſe then mad, to haue ſayd, that the declaration of baptyme had bene neceſſary for chyldren, whiche can vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande neuer a worde of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But let the wordes of my ſermond be iudge in thys matter. My wordes a lytle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the prayers were theſe.
<q>☞ And becauſe baptyſme is the ſumme of all the hole Chriſtian profeſſion, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we promyſed to beleue in Chriſt, and obey hys commaundementes: it ſhall be fytteſt for me to entreat therof. I thynke it well done, and do much prayſe, and alow the cuſtom vſed in vniuerſytes, in euerye colledge or houſe .iiij, tymes in a yeare to haue the ſtatutes lawes, and ordinaunces of theyr houſes, openly red vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by cometh great profyt vnto .ij. kyndes of ſcolars, for in euery colledge or houſe of
<pb facs="tcp:1922:12"/> learnynge, there be comonly .iij. ſortes of ſcolars: one perfyt, and well learned: the ſeconde vnperfyt, yet deſyrous and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng to attayne to the perfection: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thyrde is vtterly vnlearned, and yet neuer inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to come vnto any learnynge: To the ij. fyrſte ſortes of theſe ſcolars, is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of the lawes, and ſtatutes of their houſe verye profytable: to the perfyt, that by the often hearynge of them, they maye be by no proceſſe or lenght of tyme, forgot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten, and ſlyppe oute of theyr mynde: To the vnperfyt, yet deſyrrus, and lackyng tyme to come to perfectyon, it is very pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fytable, that the cuſtomable hearynge of the ſtatutes and lawes of theyr houſe redd before them, maye bete into theyr heades, and make them the better to knowe what ordynances be apointed for them, wherby they maye attayne to a perfectyon. And ſo are there thre kyndes of chryſten men. &amp;c. and a lytle after I ſayde theſe wordes: As to the fyrſte ſortes of ſcolers, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſall yf theyr ſtatutes is verye profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: ſo to the .ij. fyrſte ſorte of Chryſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the often readyng and repetyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſumme and abrigement of Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes is very neceſſary. for as the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes in colledges do ſhew vnto ſcholars,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> what was their founders wyll, that they ſhulde kepe: and wherunto they be bound by the lawes of theyr houſe: ſo ought we to haue an abrigement or ſumme of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes of God, to teach vs what is our duety, and what we haue bounde our ſelues to kepe.</q> When as theſe be my wordes: &amp; of them no other ſentence can be gathered: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I thought, it was as neceſſary, that bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſme (which conteyneth in it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole profeſſion of a Chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; declared, teacheth hym what is his duty, and what God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyreth of him) ſhuld be ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes reherſed, &amp; opened: as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tutes of colleges, ſhulde be red vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcolars, to put them in re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membrance, what they are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to, and what their founder re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of them: how froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and falſelye doo ye wryte my wordes: and fein, that I brynge
<pb facs="tcp:1922:13"/> them in, for to proue that chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern myghte, and oughte to be baptyſed? or if ye wyll not haue it done of malyce, and froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: I muſte nedes impute it to wonderfull great ignoraunce, and want both of wyte and lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or what learned man, replying agaynſte hys aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, whyche had holden .iij. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſyons, and made thre reſons in ordre one after an other, to confyrme hys concluſyons with all: wold aunſwer fyrſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt concluſyon: and ſay, that hys ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſaryes reaſon defending the fyrſte concluſyon, maketh not in all poyntes for the laſte conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon? In thys your doynge ye folowe verye nere a certayn vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>learned limiter of Cambrydge. Thys freer was longe and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye a daye a lymyter, and a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge
<pb facs="tcp:1922:13"/> thefe: whyche vnder the pretence of long prayer had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured the houſe of manye a poore wydowe: and whyles he dyd that, he learned nothynge but knauery. thys freer beynge olde, by the reaſon of hys age, thoughte ſhortlye to be pryor of the place: and if he were bache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of dyuynytye, he ſhuld the ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner come by his purpoſe. he gat hys grace wyth muche labour, and many promiſes, to be bache<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler of dyuynytye: but he muſte anſwer fyrſt in a dyſputation, in the dyuynytye ſchole. But the freer perceyuynge hym ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meete for that matter, came vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the doctor that ſhuld diſpute wyth hym: and deſyred hym, to be good vnto hym: and to lett him haue his arguments in wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge, and clerklye ſolutyons
<pb facs="tcp:1922:14"/> wrytten in ordre for euery argu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment: promiſing to content him for his labor, the doctor dyd ſo. but when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctor propounded the fyrſt argument in order, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of the diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had in the ſcoles: the vnlerned, and forgetfull fryar, applyed the laſt ſolution to the fyrſt argument. But the doctor ſpake merely vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the freer in theſe wordes:
<q>
                  <hi>Domine, adhuc non ſumus ibi,</hi>
               </q> Syr we are not yet there. And ſo muſt I ſaye vnto you, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring me lyke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnlearned frear. Syr we are not ſo farre as yet. anſwer fyrſt to my firſt queſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reaſons made to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them: &amp; when ye haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted them, go in hand with them, that folow in order. But let vs go forwarde, and anſwer to the reſt of the lies. Ye ſay, that I be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gan
<pb facs="tcp:1922:14"/> my ſermon with the reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuſtome of colleges, as yeare informed: pretendinge, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ye had not had not had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> copye of my ſermone before you: for this intent (as it doeth playnly apeare) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye might make a place for mo lyes, whiche ye purpoſed to bryng in by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> window: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, if any man ſhuld accuſe you for re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>herſyng any thynge hereafter, lyingly &amp; falſly: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye might ſay, I was ſo informed: as thoughe ye had learned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter only by hear ſay, &amp; not by any writyng. But the truth is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye wrote not one word againſt me, vntill y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye had my hole ſermone writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in youre handes. Therfore, yf by your information ye meane any thyng, ſauyng that ye were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by my writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſermone: ye ſwarue far from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth. the
<pb facs="tcp:1922:15"/> lye wherunto ye made a place, in youre feined information, is conteyned in theſe wordes.
<q>☞ He began firſt as I am informed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mend vnto hys audience, the cuſtome of colledges, and ſcoles in Oxforth, &amp; Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brydge, and ſuch other: where is ordeined, that ſuch as ſhall be admitted to felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp of ſuch houſes, ſhall heare the ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: whervnto they ſhall be bound .iiij. ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in the yeare, that they maye knowe their charge therby, and kepe it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ If this be not a ſhameful lye, where ye ſay that I ſpake of ſco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers, that were yet to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: I report me vnto my hole auditory: and to all them that haue red, and ſhall rede my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, faythfully gathered of me by Thomas Norton. But becauſe euery man perchaunce, can not come by my ſermond, I will repete a fewe wordes of it: which ſhall proue ye gyltie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lye, that I layde vnto youre
<pb facs="tcp:1922:15"/> charge. My words were theſe.
<q>☞ As the ſtatutes in colledges do ſhewe vnto ſcolars, what is their founders wyl, that they ſhuld kepe, and wherunto they be bounde (lo here I ſaye whereunto they be bounde, and not wherunto they ſhal be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de) by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes of theyr houſe: ſo ought we to haue an abrygement, or ſumme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commaundementes of God, to teach vs, what is our duety (I ſay not what ſhal be our duty) and what we haue bounde oure ſelues to kepe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Marke here, how that I ſay: what we haue bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d our ſelues to kepe, and not what we ſhall bynde our ſelues to kepe. Then when as my example of the rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng of the ſtatutes of coileges, foure tymes in the yeare, agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in all poyntes wyth my pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe, that I applyed it to: ye do me open wronge, to ſcourge me for your fayned and falſe forged wordes: ſayinge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my example
<pb facs="tcp:1922:16"/> doth not agree in al poyntes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my purpoſe, becauſe it agreeth not with your wordes: whiche ye bryng in after ſuch a maner, as they were myne Now ſeyng that thys playnſonge is yours, the deſcant that ye make vnto it, belongeth nothing vnto me, but ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſinge in tune, they ye offende not the eares of as cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning artificers, as you be.</p>
            <p>¶ After theſe lyes, with which ye might haue ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent, yf ye had not ben vnſatiable with ſuche: ye go faſt forwarde to bryng in mo, ſayenge:
<q>☞ That ſuch a lyke coſtome was once in our mooſt holye relygyon, as was in col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges and in orders of relygyon, wher as none were admitted, before they had a year of probation. Wher vnto ye put this that they that cam to be baptiſed, demaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, and deſyred to be receiued to the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſhip of the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s after dewe proofe
<pb facs="tcp:1922:16"/> of vnfayned repentaunce, &amp; thereby were called competentes. Yonge men, and wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men requyrynge baptyſme: and then were taught the principles of the chriſtian faith and were fyrſt called Catecumeni. And after thoſe principles learned, were vpon certayne ſolemne dayes, at two tymes of the year approued, therfore baptyſed: which was vpon eaſter euen, and wit ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day euen: promyſyng for them ſelues thob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeruaunce of Gods law, with the renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyng of the deuell and the worlde in theyr owne perſon without Godfather or god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother, ſeuen ſcore yeares longe: tyll Igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius byſhop of Rome ordened to baptyſe an infante, a godfather and godmother aunſwerynge for hym.</q> Where as ye ſay that the lyke maner was in out moſt holy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as the ſcolers and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men had: that none ſhuld be admitted, vntil they had ben proued a yeare, and firſt called competentes, and then cathecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meni.
<pb facs="tcp:1922:17"/> I maruayl what religion ye meane of: whether ye meane of the popes religion, or chriſtes religion, or of the Catabaptiſtes relygion: whiche is your religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on in dede. Yf ye mean of the ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tabaptiſtes relygyon, or the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes: it may be ſo: but thys wote I well, that it was no cuſtome in Chriſtes moſt holy relygyon. for then ſhuld we haue ſene ſom mentyon of it, ether in the actes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtels, or in the epiſtels, or goſpels. But there is no men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyon of any ſuche lyke cuſtome. Therfore ther hath ben no ſuch cuſtome in Chriſtes moſte holy religyon: except there be a moſt holy relygyon of Chriſte, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is no mentyon at all, nether in Chriſtes goſpell, nether in any part of the hole newe teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente. Chriſte neuer tyed vnto
<pb facs="tcp:1922:17"/> any time the receauinge of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme nether dyd the Apoſtles orden that at Eaſter euen, and Wytſon euen, baptiſme ſhoulde be receyued: Nay: the cuſtom of Chriſtes primatiue church, and hys Apoſtels, is contrary vnto the cuſtome vſed in your moſte holy religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For I reade in the ſecond chapter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> actes of the Apoſtles, that ther was .iiij.M men baptiſed on the ſame daye, that thei hard Peters ſermon: &amp; that without any delay. The wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture are theſe. When they had heard Peters wordes, they were prycked in their herte, and ſayde vnto Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; the other Apoſtles: what ſhall we do, ye men whyche are our brethren? Peter ſayde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: repent you of your ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: and let euery one of you be
<pb facs="tcp:1922:18"/> Baptiſed in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, to the forgeuenes of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: and ye ſhal receiue the gifte of the holy goſte, to you, and to youre chylder: and to all them that are afar of, whome ſoeuer our Lorde GOD ſhal call.</p>
            <p>And with many other wordes he witneſſed, &amp; exhorted ſayng, kepe your ſelues from this fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde nacion. Therefore they that gladly receiued the worde wer baptiſed, &amp; ther came to the churche that ſame day about .iij thouſand ſoules. How ſay you? fynde ye any mention of theſe wordes competentes, of Cathe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chumeni, of differinge baptime vnto eaſter euen, and Witſone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, or of any yere of probation? After that Philip in the .iiij. of the actes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles, had with in the ſpace of few houres dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly
<pb facs="tcp:1922:18"/> inſtructed the gelded ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Theſame ſaid vnto Philip, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaw the water: beholde here is water, what let is there but that I may be baptiſed? What wold ye haue done if that ye had bene in Philips place? it dothe appere by your writynge, that ye wolde haue aunſwered, ſyr it is the cuſtom in our moſte holy religion, to baptiſe only vpon Eaſter euen, &amp; witſonday euen: and ſuche as haue bene compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, cathecumem, and haue bene longe tyme approued: and that haue geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſufficient profe of true repentaunce: But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ye wolde haue aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Phylyp aunſwered, and dyd thus: If thou beleueſt with al thy hart, thou mayeſt be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſed, and the Enuch aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, I beleue that Ieſus Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:1922:19"/> is the ſone of God, and he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to holde ſtill the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen: and thei went both downe into the water, Philip, and the Enuch: &amp; Philip baptiſed hym. Did Philip require of this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a yere of probatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that he ſhuld be catechumes, and competen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, a greate whyle before he ſhulde be baptiſed? No forfoth. For he Baptiſed hym ſtreyght waie, wythout any delay at all. Peter in the .x. of the Actes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that his heres hadde recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the holy gooſt, ſayde theſe wordes: can there any man let, but that theſe may be baptiſed, whiche haue receyued the holy goſte as wel as we? what wold ye haue anſwered vnto S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter if ye had ben ther? It is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: that ye wold haue anſwered, lack of faith &amp; age in al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that
<pb facs="tcp:1922:19"/> are vnder the age of .xiiij. yeres and the vſe of Chriſtes primati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue churche, is to baptyſe none with ſo ſclender a trial of vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: nother is it the cuſtome in our mooſt holy reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that any that haue not ben longe tyme tryed, and haue not ben compete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes and Cathechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meni, ſhuld be baptiſed: and the time ſerueth not, for it is nother Eaſter eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor Witſonday eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wel I can not ſuerelie tel what ye wold haue anſwered, but Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter dyd commaunde them al to be Baptiſed in the name of the Lorde, thei were baptiſed with out any further delay or triall. Ananias in the .ix. Chapiter of the actes, came vnto Paule lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge his handes vpon his head, and ſeide thus. Brother Saul, the Lorde whome thou ſaweſt
<pb facs="tcp:1922:20"/> in the way, wherin thou came, hath ſent me: that thou ſhuld re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue thy ſight againe, and be fil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led with the holy goſte, &amp; forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth there fell from hys eyes, as they had bene ſcales: and he ſaw again and roſe, &amp; was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed. Howe many wekes was Paule a competentes, and how longe was he cathechumenus: Can ye proue that Ananias did differ his baptime vntil Eaſter, or witſonday? In the .xvi of the actes, Lidia was baptiſed with out any delay. The dyſciples, that were at Epheſus, and had ben only baptiſed of Iohn, with out any prolongynge of tyme, were baptiſed out of hand.</p>
            <p>It is alſo wryten of Paul, in the .xxij. of the Actes of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtels: that Ananias ſayd vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Paule, as ſone as he hadde
<pb facs="tcp:1922:20"/> receyued his ſight: why taryeſt thou? ryſe vp, and be baptiſed. It appeareth plainly, if you had be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Pauls ſtede: that ye wold haue thus holyly, and wyſely haue anſwered Ananias: what haſt? It hath bene a cuſtome long in our moſte holy religion, that no man ſhall be baptiſed, except he haue ben competens, and Cathechumenus: and haue ſhewed ſome ſuer tryall of hys vnfayned repentaunce, yet for all the cuſtom in your moſt holy religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Paul was ſtreight way baptiſed. Now ſeynge that I haue brought furth .vij. ſundrye places, and examples: to proue that the cuſtom in Chriſtes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Relygyon in the primatiue churche, was contrarye vnto the cuſtome, that ye ſayde was in youre mooſte holy relygyon
<pb facs="tcp:1922:21"/> ſeuen ſcore yeres: How ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les a lyer ye be, ye are ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared: yf that ye meane by your moſte holy religion, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. By the ſame places is your ſuperſticious admitting of men to baptim, &amp; your diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic al delaies, that Chriſtes peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple haue ben longe tryed, &amp; ben competentes &amp; Cathechumeni, vtterly confunded. Wher as ye ſay that your cuſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> endured .vij ſcore yeares, it is not true, for though Hyginus (whom ye cal very vnlearnedly Iginius) had ordened the baptiſinge of child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren (whiche I will not graunte you) yet had not youre ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous cuſtom of dilaying of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time endured ſeuen ſcore yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, for ye muſt take out the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, that goeth betwen Chriſtis byrth: and the tyme that Paule
<pb facs="tcp:1922:21"/> dyd preache: in which time wer about .xlix. yeares after Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes natiuitie at the leſte, for Chriſt was aboute, xxxiiij. yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res old, when he ſuffered. Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtels preached after Chriſtes paſſion a greate while, before Paule was conuerted: whiche beynge but yonge, kept the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes of them that flew Steue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a good while after was Paule called. Let me ſe, where youre dilayinge cuſtom can be found in Chriſtes tyme: whoſe actes and doctrine the foure E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſtes haue fully deſcribed and committed vnto writinge: and I haue proued that the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the primatiue church, is clene contrary vnto your cuſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, this is alſo approued to be true, Higinus was biſhop in Rome. An .c.xxxix. yeres by the abrige<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:1922:22"/> of Chronicles: and by Pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thalion in hys Chronographia, In .C.xi. and by Euſebius, he entred in to hys office, An. C.xlii. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had ye miſſed of recke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning, al though Higinus had or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dened the baptiſyng of childer. But it is a falſe lye: that Higi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus was he, that ordened firſt the baptiſing of childer. If that ye can clere your ſelfe, I wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, and cry you mercy. Wher is your ſufficient, and auncient author, that writeth that Higi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ordened the baptim of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der firſt? I haue read many hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, and cronicles: to ſe why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther Higinus ordened the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſyng of children, or no: but as yet I can not fynde it.</p>
            <p>Panthalion, which called his booke Chronographia, writeth thus. Higinus a Grecia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> borne,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:22"/> was in the year of oure Lorde .C.xli. and he ordened the chryſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and godfathers to bapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. The boke called <hi>epitome hyſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riarum,</hi> reporteth thus of Hygi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. Hyginus a grecian orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned chriſme, and godfathers, to the baptym of chriſten men: and the boke appoynteth to him the year of oure Lorde .C.xxix. Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rhanza the gatherer of the abry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gement of the councells, and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creees, hath theſe wordes of Hyginus. Hyginus the eyght pope, put vnto Baptym, and confirmation, a godfather and a godmother. Marke that all theſe three teſtimonies witnes not, that Hyginvs dyd ordene the Baptyme of infantes: but that he ordened to Baptyme, or put vnto Baptym Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and Godmothers.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1922:23"/>
            <p>I aſke you, to what baptim dyd Hyginus orden or put to godfa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers, and godmothers? ye wil not ſay: that de ordened godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and godmothers to old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: for that wer nothynge for your purpoſe. If ye ſay: that he ordened them, and put them to the baptyme of lpecheleſſe chyi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: then was the baptyſinge of chylder, before Hyginuſſis time Then do ye wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to ſaye, that Hyginus that pope ordened the chryſtenynge of ſpecheles chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: who only added and put to the Baptiſing of childer, chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and godfather, and godmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Now wyl I com vnto the wytneſſes of twoo great cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, the former, who is called Volaterrane, ſayeth. <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Hyginus inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit, ut Baptiſmo ſeu confirmationi unus ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem quem compatrem uocant, intereſſet.</hi>
               </q>
               <pb facs="tcp:1922:23"/> Hyginus ordened that one at the leſt, that they cal godfather, ſhude be preſented at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptime. The latter is named Platina, who wrote a propre boke, of the byſhop of Rome. His words of Higinus are theſe. <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Voluit item unum ſalte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patrimum, unam ue matrimam Baptiſmo inter eſſe. Sic enim eos appellant qui infantes tenent, dum baptizantur.</hi>
               </q> He ordened or woulde alſo, that at the leſt, one godfather or godmother, ſhould be preſente at baptyme. For ſo do they call them, whiche hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſpecheles chylder, whyles they are baptiſed. It is a greate wonder, that Hyginus ſhulde haue ordened the baptim of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fates: and none of al theſe lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned men wolde make mention of that matter, as they haue done clerely of other matters. Doutles they haue made no me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:1922:24"/> at al, in the declaringe of the deedes of Hyginus, that he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened baptyme. Then muſt I preſſe you with youre owne mannet of arguynge, whyche is thys.</p>
            <p>¶ We rede not that Chriſt, no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thet the Apoſtles ordened the baptyme of chylder. Ergo, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſte ordened, nother the Apoſtles ordened the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tym of childer. If thys be a ſuer argumente, then this that I wyl make of the ſame faſhion muſt alſo be ſuer. We rede not in their bookes that wrote the actes of Hyginus: that Higinus ordened baptym: therefore Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginus ordened not Baptym. But perchaunce ye wyl reaſon thus: he ordened godfathers, and godmothers to the bapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of chylder. This argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te
<pb facs="tcp:1922:24"/> wanteth ſtrength for the hole church, or the farer and mother maye preſent and offer vp an in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fante vnto Chriſte: and requyre ſtreyght way of thelders of the churche the Sacrament of bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme, thoughe the chryſme wer in his belly that ordened it, and the godfathers were neuer or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened. Wherfore ye wer to bold (nay to vnſhame faced) to ſay, that pope Hyginus ordened the baptyme of infantes: becauſe all men ſhuld hate it, that hate the pope.</p>
            <p>¶ Ye allege in the ende of your booke, Eraſmus, amonge a great ſorte of heretikes, which wrote agaynſt the baptim of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants: and ye alleged Eraſmus, that chylder was not baptiſed in the Apoſtels time; and it is true, that Eraſmus ſayde:
<pb facs="tcp:1922:25"/> that baptime of chyldren was not receiued in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtels tyme. for hys wordes are theſe. <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Nec ea quaeſtio tum mouebatur, quum nondum eſſet receptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pueros baptizari.</hi>
               </q> Then wyl ye ſay peraduenture: here is one learned mans opinion agaynſt you, that the baptime of childer was taken vp after the apoſtels tymes. I aunſwer you that S. Cyprian, whiche lyued and flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhed, within .cc.lvij. of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes byrth: and Saynt Auſten, which liued but .CCCC.xlij. after Chriſtes natiuite, affirmed both, that the baptiſyng of chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der came vnto vs from the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels handes: and Eraſmus ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth that the baptime of childer was nod receiued in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels times. Whether is it more mete to beleue? Cypryan, and Auſten whiche were ſo nere the
<pb facs="tcp:1922:25"/> Apoſtles tyme: or Eraſmus, whiche lyued and dyed in oure dayes? What wyll ye anſwere? Aunſwer what ye wyll, I wyll make Eraſmus by hys owne ſentence and reaſon pronounce, that Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Cyprian are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be beleued in ſuche lyke matter, then he is. Eraſmus beyng ſumthing offended with Chryſoſtome, whyche denyed Paule had a wyfe, wrote theſe wordes.
<q>
                  <hi>Chryſostomus fatetur fuiſſe, qui putarent hic Paulu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appellare ſuam uxorem: ſed diſſentit: nec cauſam reddit, cur diſſentiat. Sed utris potius aequu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt accedere Clementi, &amp; Ignatio, quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ille Petri comes fuit, hic Marci Euangelistae diſcipulus: &amp; Chryſostomo, qui tanto inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uallo ſemotus fuit a temporibus apostolorum.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Chryſoſtome graunteth: that there were ſome, that thought that Paule in thys place, ſpake
<pb facs="tcp:1922:26"/> ſpake vnto hys wyfe: but he thynketh otherwyſe, &amp; yet ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth no cauſe why. But whether of thes is it meter, that we ſhuld beleue, Clement, and Ignaty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, of the whych, the one was Peters companyon, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the dyſcyple of Marke the Euangeliſt: or Chryſoſtome, whyche was ſo longe a tyme from the tyme of the Apoſtles? Thys may be gathered of theſe wordes: he is more worthy cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in bearyng of wytnes, that is nerer the dede, when it is done: or nerer the tyme, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was done. Whervpon I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude thus. Auſten, Cypriane, and Orygen, were nerer the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles tymes, then Eraſmus was, therfore Auſten, and Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryane, are more to he beleued, whyche wrote, that baptyme
<pb facs="tcp:1922:26"/> came from the Apoſtles: then Eraſmus, whych ſayd, that bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſyng of chyldren was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued in the Apoſtles tymes. Here are ye dyſapoynted of one of your poſtes, that ye lened to in your opynyon, that the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme of chyldren was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued in the Apoſtles tymes. But leſte ye ſhoulde thynke, that Auſten, and Cyprian, we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re not of that mynde, wherof I report them to be: I wyll rehearſe yow Saynt Auſtens wordes in the fourth boke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Donatiſtes of the bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſing of chyldren, in the fourth chapter.
<q>
                  <hi>Et ſi quis<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>quam</ex>
                     </expan> in hacre autoritatem diuinam quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat: quan<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>quam</ex>
                     </expan> quod uniuerſa tenet eccleſia, nec conciliis inſtitutum, ſed ſemper retentum est:
<pb facs="tcp:1922:27"/> non niſi autoritate apostolica traditum rectiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſime creditur.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>That is, If any man loke for the autorite of God in this mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. Howbeit, that which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole churche holdeth, and is not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened of any counſell, but is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes holden ſtyll: it is mooſte ryghtlye beleued, that it was geuen oute and ordened by the Apoſtles. The ſame Auſten in a ſermonde of the baptyſme of infantyng agaynſt the Pelagy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aus, ſayth theſe wordes: Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priane beyng axed, whether an infant myghte be baptyſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the viij. daye: becauſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde lawe, the childe myght not be cyrcumcyſed, but on the ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte day: Saint Cyprian ſaid: that no man ſhulde be hyndred from grace, and that the ſpiry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual cyrcumcyſyon oughte not
<pb facs="tcp:1922:27"/> to be hyndred by carnall cyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcyſyon. Cypriane wryteth alſo in the viij. epiſtel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrd booke, theſe wordes, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the baptyme of infantes.
<q>
                  <hi>Porro autem ſi etiam grauiſsimis delictoribus, &amp; in deum multum ante peccatibus, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſtea crediderunt, remiſsio peccatorum datur: &amp; ae baptiſmo, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> gratia nemo prohibetur: quanto magis prohiberi non debet infans, qui recens natus, peccauit: niſi quòd ſecundum Adam car naliter natus, contagium mortis antiqua prima natiuitate contraxit?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore, but yf that forgeuenes of ſynnes, be geuen vnto the greateſt ſynners, and to them, that dyd greately of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend before, after that they dyd beleue: and no man is forbyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> baptyme &amp; grace: How much more ought not a ſpechles chylde to be forbydden, whych
<pb facs="tcp:1922:28"/> beyng lately borne, hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted no offence: but that it beyng borne carnally after A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam hath caught the infeccyon of the olde death, by hys fyrſt byrthe? This is the mynde of Cypryane, concernyng bapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of chylder, and of originall ſynne. And the ſame doctor wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth in an other place.
<q>
                  <hi>Nos iure damnamus omnia, quae Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus non docuit.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>We condemne by good ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght all thynges, whych Chriſte hath not taught. But Cypry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane alowed the baptyme of chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dern, therfore he reckened, that the baptyſyng of chyldren was taught of Chriſt. That Origen is of that iudgement, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme of chylder came from the Apoſtels, hys wordes vpon the epyſtle to the Romanes, and
<pb facs="tcp:1922:28"/> vpon Iohan, do clearly teſtyfy: as hereafter I ſhall proue, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhall come to the place, where as ye alledge Orygen your ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Now ſeyng that theſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble learned men, whych were ſo nere hand the tymes of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, holde in theyr workes with the baptyme of infantes, and ſaye that it came vnto vs from the Apoſtles: what wyſe man wyll rather beleue yow, beynge ſo longe after the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles tymes, then them, whych were ſo long ago, and ſo nere the tymes of the Apoſtels? Ye haue therefore long and beſely babled in vain, holding without any autorytye, and agaynſt lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng, and authoritye, that the Pope ordened fyrſt the bapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of infantes. And ſo ye haue
<pb facs="tcp:1922:29"/> won nothyng, ſauyng that ye haue founde and made a rodde for your owne tayle. I meane that I haue gotten and gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of your aſſertyon and opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyon, a good coniectural argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the baptyme of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes came from thapoſtles ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes. For ye ſhewed me fyrſte, that Hyginus ordened the bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme of infantes: which Hygi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus (as I ſhall declare hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) was but .xxxviij. yeares fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome of thapoſtles. For Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terane wryteth in hys boke, cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led Anthropologia: that Saint Ihon the Euangelyſt lyued vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the .lxviii. yeare after the paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt, hys wordes are theſe. <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Ioannes longa ſenectute confectus,</hi> 68. <hi>anno post Chriſti ſupplicium extinctus eſt.</hi>
               </q> And Chriſt was .xxxiiij. yeares olde, when he ſuffred, therefore
<pb facs="tcp:1922:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> Iohan beyng alyue .lxviij. after hys paſſyon, was alyue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 102. yeare after Chriſtes byrth.</p>
            <p>And Hyginus was 140. yeares after Chriſtes byrth. therfore Higinus, and ſome of the apoſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les, namely ſaint Iohn the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geliſt, were no more one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, then xxxviij. yeares. Whereby, thorow youre helpe. I haue now proued, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſynge of yonge chyldren was vſed wythin .xxxviij. yeares of ſome of the Apoſtles tymes. I haue alſo proued by good aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytye, that Hyginus dyd not orden the baptyſynge of chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: and that he onlye put and added to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptyme of chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, chriſme, &amp; godfather, &amp; godmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wherfore the baptyſyng of chyldren beyng before Higi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſſes tymes: and ſeynge he
<pb facs="tcp:1922:30"/> ſeynge he was with in .xxxviij. yeres of ſome of the Apoſtelles tymes: it is a probable, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lykelye thynge: that the bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſyng of childer came vnto vs, euen from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtels: who were but a very ſhorte tyme before. Ye are diſapoynted of your pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe, whych thought to haue brought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptyſynge of ſpech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les chylder, into a great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt, &amp; an vtter deſpyſyng: becauſe it had ben, as ye thought, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes ordenyng, &amp; makyng: yf ye had not be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proued an arra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lier. but ye are proued a lyer, wher ye ſayd, that Hygynus ordened the baptim of infants, and an ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gument of antiquite is gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the longe contynuaunce of chylders baptyme, and of the long approbatyon of the ſame, thorow oute all hole Chriſtes
<pb facs="tcp:1922:30"/> churche: which is more worthy to be admitted, then your ſuper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſticious opinion, whoſe author was that perilous heritike Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lagius: whom in thende of your boke, ye bryng in right honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly for a wytnes, to mayntayne your dyueliſhe opinion.</p>
            <p>But although Hyginus had ordened firſt, that childer ſhuld be baptiſed, yet ſhulde not their baptyme haue bene Popyſhe, for in the tyme of Hyginius, the byſhops of Rome, had not yet vſurped any ſupremacie ouer other Byſhops: muche leſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Kynges, and Emperours. Neyther hadde the byſhops of Rome brought in the dyuelyſhe doctryne, wherefore theyr doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine was hated and called po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſhe and dyuelyſhe. In the tyme of Hyginus euery byſhop
<pb facs="tcp:1922:31"/> was called Papa, as euery preſt in hygh Almony is called pfaff: and in low Germany pape, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto thys day. Wherefore the doynge of Hyginus, ſhuld haue no more ben called popyſh, then the ordynaunce of any other by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhopp, that dwelt out of Rome, ether in Aſia, or Aphrica. How be it, thankes be vnto God, I haue had wytnes ynough, to proue that the baptyme of yong chyldren was not ordened of Hi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginus: and lo, can the baptyme of chyldren, in no wyſe be called popyſh, as we call ſuche as yow Popyſh: whych, at the laſt eſter, right Popiſhly knelyng, toke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrament, geuyng occaſyon vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to all men to thynke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye were a ſterke ydolater, and beleued, that bread was turned into a God. For your doyng was the
<pb facs="tcp:1922:31"/> ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of a lofty, and a right Antichriſtian byſhop of Rome: whiche vſurped power, both o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all byſhops, and alſo ouer al Kynges and Emperours. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I haue, with the reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of .vii. places of ſcripture, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficiently reproued your folyſhe, and monkiſh maner, in dilaying of baptime: your tyrannical ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it vp vnto certayne tymes: and that your Cathechumeni, with their yeares of probation, are contrary to the vſe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes primatiue church, yet for to proue that youre dylaying of baptime: whereupon ye wolde grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de your erroure, that chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ought not to be baptiſed, is agaynſt the ſcripture, and only the ordinaunce of men: I wyll ſhew, what men, and what cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, haue ordened all your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes:
<pb facs="tcp:1922:32"/> that al men may perceiue eaſely: that ye buylde not vpon Chriſt, but vpon Popes men, and councels. Who wolde haue thought before this, that cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtry wolde haue leaned v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon any ſuche foundacions? Ye hadde wont to rattel, and crake nothing but ſcripture, ſcripture but now, for lacke of ſcriptur, ye make theſe councels, and lawes of man, your foundacion. It is wryten in the Laodicen coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, in the .xlv. Chapter of them that come to be baptiſed aboute the mydweke.
<q>
                  <hi>Non oportet, poſt duas hebdomadas quadrage ſimae, quenquam ad baptiſmum ſuſcipi.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>After twoo weakes of lente, muſte none bee receyued vnto baptyme: In the ſame counſell, it is wrytten, of the rendrynge of the belief of them that ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:1922:32"/> baptiſed in the .xxv. Chapiter. They that ſhall bee baptyſed, muſt learne the Crede: and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the thurſdaye of the laſte weke, to ad or preſent them to the Byſhop or elder. The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin wordes are theſe. <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Baptizandos oportet fidei ſymbolum diſcere: &amp; quinta feria ultimae ſeptimanae, uel Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po uel preſbytero addere.</hi>
               </q> This counſel was holden in the tyme of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius the Biſhop of Rome, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yere of our lord .CCC ixiiij. In the Gerunden cuncell, in the third ſtatute, it was orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Vt cathechumeni baptizentur, die uel uigilia Paſchae &amp; Pentecoſtes: caeteris ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatibus tantum infirmi,</hi>
               </q> that is: that the diſciples, or learners, called Cathechumeni, ſhuld be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, on eaſter day, or eaſter euen or witſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day, or witſon eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:1922:33"/> other ſolemne dayes, let only them that are ſycke be baptiſed This counſel was holden in the tyme of Hormiſda, Byſhop of Rome, in the yere of our Lord D.xiij. Siritius byſhop of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: whiche lyued in the yere of our Lord .CCC.lxxxix. orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in hys ſeconde decree, that baptim ſhulde not be miniſtred, but at Eaſter and Witſondaye. The latin is this, <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Statuit Siritius, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>quam</ex>
                     </expan> in Paſcha, &amp; Pentecoſte baptiſmus non celebretur.</hi>
               </q> This was alſo ordened in the fourth councell of Carta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge: that they, that were to bee baptiſed, ſhulde ſhew theyr na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and abſteyne a longe tyme from wine, and fleſhe: that they ſhulde haue handes layd vpon theyr heades: and be oft exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: and then receyue baptime. The latin is thus in the .lxxxv
<pb facs="tcp:1922:33"/> chapter of the foreſayd counſel <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Baptizandi nomen ſuum dent, &amp; diu ſub abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentia uini &amp; carninm, ac manus impoſitione, crebra examinatione baptiſmum precipiant.</hi>
               </q> Here is the foundacion: where vpon ye buylde your delaying denyall, ye rather the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the baptim of infantes. Vpon theſe counſels, and mens decrees, are buylded your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtened Cathechumeni your deueliſſhe delaying of baptime: your tyinge vp of it to certayne tymes, as to Eaſter, and Wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſondaye. Here is grounded the cuſtome of dylayinge, and dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge of, of baptime: whiche ye very lyinglye, lyke a man paſt al ſhame, ſayde, was in oure moſte holy religion vſed, ſeuen ſcore yeres: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as al theſe autours and councellers, whyche orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned theſe dylays, were many
<pb facs="tcp:1922:34"/> yeres after the time of Hygini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us who was aboute ſeuen ſcore yeres after Chriſtes natiuite. How vnſhamefacedly then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ye aſſygned that cuſtome of dylayinge of baptime, vnto the tyme, that went betwene Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes natiuite and Hyginus: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge that theſe dylayes was ordened .CC. yeres and more, after Chriſtes byrth? Why do ye refuſe to fight with me, with ſuche weapons, as I brought into the fielde? I brought in the ſworde of Goddes worde, to defende the baptyme of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der withall: for I defended it only with the worde of GOD. But ye now, wryting agaynſt me, fyght agaynſt the baptime of chylder, wyth no ſcripture: but wyth cuſtomes, wyth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, councels, ordynaunces
<pb facs="tcp:1922:34"/> of men, the autoritie of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſtes, Anabaptiſtes, and Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lagians, all open heretikes, and worthelye condemned of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes hole churche. As for theſe wepons, I fet not one ſtrawby: for all theſe can not preuayle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the worde of GOD. Thynke you, that when I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue defended my doctryne with ſcripture, that your vnſauery reaſons, grounded vpon coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and men, can confute my reaſons, grounded vpon the holy ſcripture? Whoſoeuer go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth aboute to confute ſcripture with councels and mens decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and hys owne argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: preferreth counſels, and decrees before GOD, and his worde, and reckeneth hym ſelfe better then GOD. In my ſermon at Thyſtelworth, I
<pb facs="tcp:1922:35"/> reſoned thus ſtrongly armed with the authoritie of ſaint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in the .x. of the Actes of the Apoſtels. There is nothynge that can hynder them to be bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſed, which haue the holy goſte chylder haue receyued the holy goſte as wel as olde men: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is nothynge to hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, but they may be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, as wel as olde folke: ye, to confute that chylder ſhulde be baptiſed, brynge in agaynſte my alleged ſcripture, the longe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom in your moſte holy church, councels and decrees of Pree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes and byſhops: wherefore ye prefer them before GOD and hys open ſcrypture: and ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken mannes cuſtome ſtronger, then Goddes worde, and man ſtronger then GOD, for that doth euery man reeken ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:35"/> whyche can ouercome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Then ye confutynge my alledged ſcrypture, mans doctryne, haue a very euyll o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion agaynſt GOD, and his worde, much lyke vnto the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes whych deſtitute of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, fought after thys maner ar ye do now. Whereas ye hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de that.
<q>Where men and wemen of perfyt age are baptiſed, all the three ſortes of ſcolares ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke profite of the openynge, and declaryng of baptyme: but when as childer are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſed, none of them all, for ye ſaye, when men and wemen are baptiſed, all receyue admoniſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: by which the good amend and theyr lyues, and are ſaued: the other knowynge, that they ſtonde bounde ſtyll to amende or to be condemned.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Ye aunſwere me very fryar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, lewdlye, vnlearnedly, and
<pb facs="tcp:1922:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> lyingly. Firſt it is playnly aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt al ſcripture, and reaſon that he that lyueth noughtely, and neuer intendeth to amend hys lyfe, after that he is baptyſed (for of ſuche ſpake I) ſhall bee anye thynge the better by the ſeynge of the baptyme of men and weme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: namely, the caſe put before, that the thyrde ſorte, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was chriſtian in lyuynge, nether inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to lyue any chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian lyfe. Can the ſyghte of a Sacrament alone, be it neuer ſo well minyſtred, profite hym that neuer intendeth to profit? Wyll the worke of ſeynge bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme wrought make hym that intendeth no Godlynes be god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye? Is not thys to ſaye, that wheate ſowen vpon a ſtone ſhal ryue the ſtoone, and make it brynge furthe fruyte, whether
<pb facs="tcp:1922:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> it wyl or no, agaynſte the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of the ſtone? So that ye ſaye wyttely, and wyſelye that it pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fiteth al the three ſortes: the is, them of the perfiteſt ſorte, them that are vnperfit, and deſire per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fection: and them that nother are perfyt, nor yet intende to come to any perfection. Of the lyke foolyſhnes is your ſaying: that where as chyldern ar bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyſed, no man taketh profyt: wherof? of the chyldes bapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, or of the openyng and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarynge of our baptime, which are baptyſed alredy? If that ye mene, that in that congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where as children are baptiſed, the declarynge of the myſtery, and ſecretes of oure baptyme profyteth nothynge vnto ſuch men, as the ſcripture calleth lytel ones, that is lowlye in
<pb facs="tcp:1922:37"/> ſprete, and haue the conditions of yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge chylder: ye holde playn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly againſt this open text of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture. <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Declaratio ſermonum tuorum illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, &amp; intellectum dat paruulis.</hi>
               </q> The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of thy wordes lyghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and giueth vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to the lytle ones, whervpon we may gather that thoſe, that are not lytel ones, but ſtubborne withſtanders, can haue no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyt by the declaration of Gods word, much leſſe by the ſeynge of men and wymen baptyſed. If ye mene that where as chylder are baptyſed, that nother the chylde hathe any profyt by the baptym and offeryng vp of it vnto Chriſt: nother they that offer it vp, nother they that ſee the baptime miniſtred, take any profyt therby: ye ſpeke agaynſt the ſcripture. For the chylder
<pb facs="tcp:1922:37"/> get Chriſtes blyſſynge: yf he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue chylder yet, as wel as he had wont to do: and the offerers &amp; bryngers of childer vnto chriſt, in doyng of a good dede, profyt, for he that helpeth a man to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue a good turne, in helpyng, doth profit in godlynes: and na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mely they that pray to the lord, eyther for the bodely or goſtly health of theyr neyghbour? Did not both the bringers of the chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren vnto Chriſt, and the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der profyt alſo before Chriſtes paſſion? Is he wexed vngentler after his paſſion, then he was before? The chyrche at the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſinge of chylder, prayeth vnto God for the childe, that it maye haue forgiueniſſe of ſynnes, and receyue the holy goſte, wyl God breke his promyſſe, that he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vnto his churche, <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Quicquid pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticritis
<pb facs="tcp:1922:38"/> patrem in nomine meo, dabit uobis.</hi>
               </q> What ſoeuer ye ſhal are my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in my name, he wyll geue it. The father and mother, with the hole chyrche, prayeth for the yonge chylde, at the baptiſyng of it: other they profyt, or God is falſe: but he is true, therefore ye ar a lyer, whiche ſaye, that where as chylder are baptiſed, that nother the chylde, nor any that, ar there at the baptim, and offer the chyld vnto Chriſte, with theyr prayers, profyt any thynge at al. What more profyt ſhal the ſeers of the baptym of men and wemen, take thereby then the ſeers of the baptime of chyldern? Seyng that all that is doone to olde folke, is alſo doone vnto chylder: &amp; the word of GOD as well al red, and preched at childers baptim, as
<pb facs="tcp:1922:38"/> at old folkes baptime: they that are at the baptiſyng of chylder, profyt as muche, as they that are at olde folkes baptym. Whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re as the ſygnes and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes are al one: &amp; the worde of GOD is alyke preached: the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re cometh vnto the herers, and ſeers lyke profyt: except GOD be a regarder of perſons, and be better vnto olde men, then vnto chyldern: whyles he graunteth profyt, and grace to the ſeers of olde folkes baptyme: and none at all to the ſeers of chylders baptyme: but God regardeth no perſons, therfore ther is lyke profyt, in ſeing of other of both. Of lyke thyngs ought to be ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke iugement, then when as bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tym is all one in ſignification wyth cyrcumcyſion: and they that ſee chylder cyrcumciſed,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:39"/> haue as muche profyt by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therof, as of the ſeing of old folke circumciſed: ſo the ſeers of the baptyme of chylder haue as muche profyt thereby, as the ſeers of the baptyme of olde fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. In the beginning of your boke, ye ſaide that I reherſed the .iiij. tymes redyng of ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in colledges, to proue that yoing ſpecheles childer might and ought to be baptyſed: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſayinge, howe falſe &amp; lying it was, I haue ſufficientlye pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued. And nowe lyke a deuyll, that for hys purpoſe turnethe hym ſelfe into all colours and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures: here ye ſay, that I applie the coſtom of readyng of the ſco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lars ſtatutes, that infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſhuld haue the declaration of baptym preached vnto them. Theſe are your wordes.
<pb facs="tcp:1922:39"/>
               <q>☞ Therfore to rede the ſtatutes to infan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes is of no exemple nor value, but to them that be growen it is an occaſion to get ſcolers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Couche, of thy conſcyen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce (yf thou haſte any at all) tell me whether thou knoweſte in thy conſcience, or no: that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſed, and applied the reading of ſcolares ſtatutes: vnto the baptyſyng of yong chyldern: or that ſpecheles chylder ſhoulde haue baptyme opened vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by preachynge: or els that I brought that cuſtome furth in very deede: to ſhew them, that were my hearers (amonge the which was not one ſpecheles childe) that it were as neceſſary for them, to haue theyr baptime opened, and declared by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng: as it was neceſſarye for ſcolars, to haue theyr ſtatutes
<pb facs="tcp:1922:40"/> at certayn tymes to be redde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them? If thou knouweſt not this in thy conſcience: ether the deuyll hath blynded the wyth malice, or thou art ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, and folyſh: that thou art more worthy to haue a muk forke in thy hande, then a pen to wryte agaynſt any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſeyng the matter is ſo clearly ſet out, without any rydles, or para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. If thou doeſt know in thy conſcience: that I reherſed this example, nether to proue the ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptyme of chylder wyth all, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that chyldren ſhulde haue baptyme declared vnto them: and that onlye they, that can vnderſtand, and the openynge of baptyme, ſhoulde haue it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to theym: what deuyll art thou poſſeſſed withal which to defende thy folyſh opinyon,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:40"/> writeſt vtterly agaynſt thy con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience? But thys miniſheth my meruelynge, that I cal now to remembraunce: whiche chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vnto me at Anwarpe. I rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoned with one of your ſecte, at Anwarpe: who was learned in the Latyn tongue, a doctor of phiſicke, and a greate Alchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſte, when as we wete both chafed, and heted with the long diſputation: he defending here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſye, and I confutynge theſame: at lenght, I toke hym with a ſhamfull lye, and with ſuche a contradiction in his tale: that he coulde not deny, but that it was ſo. But howe dyd he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe hym ſelfe? verelye thus. It is wryten, ſayeth he, in the xviij. of the Apocalyps: that we ſhuld handle the, and ſuch as thou art, the whors chylder of
<pb facs="tcp:1922:41"/> Babylon, with lyes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all other ſuche lyke, for the reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gynge of the lyes, that ye haue made vnto vs in tymes paſt, the wordes of Ihon, ſayeth he, are theſe.
<q>
                  <hi>Reddidit illi, ſicut &amp; ipſa reddidit uobis, &amp; duplicate ei duplicia ſecundum opera eius.</hi>
               </q> That is, Rendre, or gyue agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnto hyr, as ſhe hath rendred to you: and duble the duble vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hyr, accordynge vnto hyr workes. And when I alledged the ſcripture vnto him, that the lying mought kylled the ſoule: he anſwered, that it was true in ſuch, as me that had no fayth: but that it was not ſo in hym, that had the true fayth, and was of the true religion: alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging this place of ſcripture for hym.
<q>
                  <hi>Si quid lethale biberint, non nocebit eis.</hi>
               </q>
               <pb facs="tcp:1922:41"/> yf they drynke any dedly poyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it ſhall not hurte them, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundyng it thus: there can no lyinge, nether any other ſin, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is poyſon, vnto your ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, hurt vs, which beleue as we bo. Terfore ſeyng that ye call me, and al other, that defend the baptym of chylder, papiſtes, that is the chylder of the hoore of Babylon: and ſeparate your ſelfe both in the ſupper of our Lorde, and alſo in baptyme, and in the vnderſtandyng of origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſin, from vs: and make your ſelfe of an other religion: it is no meruel, that ye handle me euen ſo here in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, as your brother catabaptiſt handled me in Anwerp. And whete as men haue ſuch conſcience, that they care not what they do, ſo that it be done ſecretly vnto any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:1922:42"/> of another religion: whether it be yeoperdous for me, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediente for the rulers of this realm, to haue ſuch nere hand or no the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I reporte me vnto all wyſe, &amp; godly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Much vayne bablynge, and vnprofitable com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munication, as vnworthy any aunſwere, do I paſouer: and come vnto the place, where as ye ſay: that baptym is to my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes (for ſo do ye call them) and vnbeleuers, a vayn &amp; bare ſygne, vnfruitfull and vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: except I wyll gyue, and aſſygne vertue vnto the worke wrought. Where as ye make all infantes myne, becauſe I take in hand tho defende theyr bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tym: I may a great dele be leſſe aſhamed of my poore, and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente infantes, then ye maye be, to defende the doctryne of your
<pb facs="tcp:1922:42"/> ſedytions, and mourderynge Anabaptiſtes: which deſtroyed the noble citie of Munſter, in Weſphali: and roſe vp agaynſt the Magiſtrates, in Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam: and wan Swol, not far from Dauenter: and were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to haue deſtroyed Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge, in Weſt Freſelande. Let the innocentes be myne ſtyll, and let the factious cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtes be yours. Let ſe, who ſhal be more aſhamed in the great daye of them, that they defende. But ſeynge ye wyll nedes make the infantes myne, I wyll defende them as well as I can: for as much as euery man is bounde to defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de it, that is hys. My infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes are not vtterly withoute all faythe, as ye meane, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge them vnbeleuers.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1922:43"/>
            <p>This wyll I proue by your owne maner of alledginge the ſcripture, in the middes of your boke agaynſte me. What ſoeuer is not of fayth, is ſynne, nothyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge that the infant doth, or thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth: wheter it ſukketh milke, or drynketh bere, or ale, or cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth fleſh, as ye holde, is of fayth, for fayth is of heatynge, and heatynge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>methe by that worde of GOD, then they the heare not the worde of GOD, as chylder do not, can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng, of fayth, wherfore by your own alledging of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, the childe doth nothynge: but it ſynneth in doynge, what ſo euer it dooth, for lacke of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yth. But that they ſin not in all thyng, and that they ar not wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hout all fayth, I proue it thus. They pleaſe GOD: therefore
<pb facs="tcp:1922:43"/> they at not without al fayth, for Paule ſayeth: without fayth it is impoſſible tho pleaſe GOD. That ſpecheleſſe chylder, haue pleaſed GOD: Iacob, Hieremy the Prophete, and Iohan the Baptiſt are wytneſſes. So ar alſo the chylder, that Chriſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke in his armes, wytneſſes of the loue, that Chriſt bare vnto chylder. Marke wytneſſeth, that Chriſte toke the chylder in to his armes, and blyſſed them. If that he blyſſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed hym, If they pleaſed hym, they were not without faith, ye do therfore the poore innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes great wronge, in callyng them vnbeleuers. At the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vnbeleeuing? Ye ſay, yea, then haue they that vnbeleeuin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge, and want of faythe: ether of their firſt creation, or by Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:1922:44"/> fall. yf that they haue it by their fyrſt creation: it is not true, that God ſayd, that all thyng whych he had made, was verye good. Is an vnbeleuyng man verye good? Is that good, whych can not pleaſe God? If that chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be vnbeleuyng by Adams fall, then haue we found agayne orygynall ſynne, which ye with your mayſter Pellagius do vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deny. Ye ſaye that they are vnbeleuyng, and wythout faith: but how proue ye that? If ye ſay: I ſe no workes yet in chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: therfor, they haue no faith: I axe yow, whether ye are a beleuer, or vnbeleuer, when ye are a ſlepe, and at al tymes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye do no good workes? yf ye do beleue, when ye are a ſlepe, and at other tymes, when ye do no good workes: ſo maye chyldren
<pb facs="tcp:1922:44"/> haue faith, although they be not yet come vnto the tyme of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claryng of fayth by theyr wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. Is there any man ſo foliſh, or ſo cruel, that wyll call a yong gryfte of the fyrſte yeres gryf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge fruytles, and barro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it can not for lacke of tyme &amp; age, brynge as yet furth anye fruyte? If that we can not call a tree vnfruytefull, vntyll the tyme come of bryngynge furth of fruyte: ſo ought ye not to call a chylde vnbeleuyng, &amp; faithles: vntyll he come vnto the time of declaryng his fayth. I axe you. <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Estne puer animal rationale, an non?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Whether is a chylde a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable liuing thyng, or no? If ye graunt, that he is an vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable creature: then ye make a chylde, a brute beaſte, yf that a child be a reaſonable creature, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:1922:45"/> yet can not for lacke of time and age, vſe reaſon: ſo maye a chylde haue fayth, and be called fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: though for lacke of tyme and age, it can ſhewe as yet no good workes: whych are the to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kens, and fruytes of fayth. If ye reaſon that they know not, that they haue fayth, therefore they haue no fayth: I reaſon wyth you agayn chylder know not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are redemed wyth Chriſtes bloude: ſhall we ſaye therfore, that chyldren are not redemed with Chriſtes bloud? Chyldren know not, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys of ſaluatyon belongeth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to them: ſhall we ſay therefore that the promys of ſaluatyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyneth not vnto chyldren? Is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heyre of landes heyre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he knowe, that he is heyre? So maye a chylde haue fayth,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:45"/> and yet for lacke of age knowe not, that it hath it. Becauſe ye alledge the ſcrypture hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, generallye, and delyuer it from all cyrcumſtances: ye muſt ſuffer me to reaſon wyth you af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame maner, at this time. Anſwer me to this argument. Children are not already conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned: therfore they do beleue. for the ſcripture ſayth, he that bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not, is condemned alredy. Therfore ye muſt ether grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that chylder do beleue, or elles, that they are already condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Chylder alſo haue the holy ghoſt. Is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt wythout fayth? They haue all thynges, that Chriſt hath: for they are Chriſtes. &amp; he that ſpared not hys only ſonne, as Paule ſayth, but delyuered hym vp for vs, (and for chylder as well, as for
<pb facs="tcp:1922:46"/> old men) it is impoſſyble, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he gaue all thyng vnto chylder wyth Chriſt. how can chyldren be faythleſſe, whych haue all, that Chriſt hath? Was Chriſt without fayth? Now, whether your (I ſay) or my argumentes are worthy more credence, let them that are faithful men, iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge indifferently. But what yf I graunted you, that chyldren had no fayth: yet it dyd not fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infantes ſhuld haue no fruyte of theyr baptyme. For our infantes are in as good a caſe, as the infantes of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes were in the ſame age, that oure infantes are of. But thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gh they hadde bene wythout fayth, yet had they receyued theyr cyrcumcyſyon wyth fruit and profyte, euen ſo thoughe oure chyldren were wythoute
<pb facs="tcp:1922:46"/> fayth, they ſhulde receyue their baptyme w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as great fruyte, as the Hebrues chylder receyued theyr circumciſyon. for that is baptim vnto vs, that was cyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes. Our baptyme, and the cyrcumcyſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are all one ſpirytually, and in ſignyfycatyon, and onely do differ in the elementes. Al they that were receyued into the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt, made to the fathers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde teſtament, were cyrcumcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and therby were receyued into the felowſhip of the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> promys: ſo all they that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into the couenante made to vs of the new teſtament, are by baptyme receiued into oure church &amp; feloſhip: and haue it among vs as a ſeale of Goddes promys vnto vs, as the Iewes had cyrcumcyſyon as a ſygne of
<pb facs="tcp:1922:47"/> theyr couenaunt among them. Cyrcumcyſyon requireth a cyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcyſed hart, and a new lyfe: &amp; that all they that are cyrcumcy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, ſhuld mortifye all carnall af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fectyons, noughty luſtes, and fleſhlye deſyres. Therfore the prophetes laying to the Iewes charges, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they aunſwered not vnto theyr profeſſion, call them vncyrcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harte. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth the lord ſpeake thus of the Iewes. Leuit. 26. I ſhall bryng them into their enemies land: that then at the length, theyr vncyrcumcyſed hart may ſubmitte it ſelfe, and humble it. Hieremy wryteth thus vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes. Be ye circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde: and take awaye the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyrcumciſyon of your hart. And almlghty God in Moſes ſpake after the ſame maner. Deut. 10.
<pb facs="tcp:1922:47"/> Circumcyſe and cut away the ſkynne, or vncyrcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion of your harte: and harden youre necke no more. In all theſe places is mortifycatyon requyred of the cyrcumcyſed: as Paule in the ſyxte to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romanes requireth mortifycation, where he ſayth. Do ye not know, that all we y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are baptyſed into Chriſt Ieſu, ar baptyſed into hys death? Therfore we are buryed wyth hym thorow baptime into hys death: that as Chriſte was ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp from the ded, by the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the father, we ſhuld walke in newenes of lyfe. Then as cir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cumciſyon layd vpon the ſpech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les chyldern of the Iewes is a profeſſyon of mortificatyon, and profiteth the chyldern: not for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke wrought, but for the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundementes ſake, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe
<pb facs="tcp:1922:48"/> of God: So is the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of baptyme layd vpon our yonge chyldren, a profeſſyon of mortifycatyon, and profyteth them not thorowe the wrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght worcke it ſelfe, but thorow the promyſſe of GOD and hys worde: and the promyſſe that he made to hys holy churche: and the prayers made by the churche. ye ſay that.
<q>☞ When as men and wymen are baptyſed, all men take admonyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, by whych the good amend their lyues and are ſaued.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ When as men, and wymen are baptyſed, I axe you: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they that are baptyſed are ſaued thorowe the promys of God made vnto them, or tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row theyr worthynes of recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge of baptym: or by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke
<pb facs="tcp:1922:48"/> wrought in hearyng or ſeyng of the admouyſhement, that commeth of baptyſynge of men, and wymen: If ye ſaye: that your men, and wymen haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſyon of ſynnes by receyuing of baptyme at ſuch an age: then do not they receyue forgyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſynnes, and the hery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by the promys, but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a worke wrought ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely in ſuch an age. If they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the herytage, and forgyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſynnes by the promys: then chylder hauyng the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys as well, as men, &amp; wymen, maye haue remiſſyon of ſynne, when as they are baptyſed, as well as olde folke. For GOD hath no reſpecte of perſones, &amp; regardeth not one age more then an other. Do not ye gyue vertue to the worke wrought.
<pb facs="tcp:1922:49"/> when ye ſay that men are ſaued by the admonyſhment, of ſeyng men &amp; wymen baptyſed? Wher dyd God promyſe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeers of men and wymens baptyme, ſhould be ſaued therby? Where did God orden, that the only ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of baptim ſhould cauſe men amend their liuyng, and therby be ſaued? yf God made no ſuche promys: why do you gyue ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of ſaluation, vnto the worke wroughte: whych God neuer ordened any ſaluatyon to come by? Who is now the iuſticyari? Who is he now, that geueth not only vertue, but alſo the vertue of amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of lyfe, and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the work wrought of an onloker, &amp; onli a ſear of baptim? What deſerueth an old man, by hys cyrcumcyſion in hys age, more then a chyld deſerueth by
<pb facs="tcp:1922:49"/> his circumciſion receiued in the viij. daye after hys natiuite? If neither of both deſerueth more then another: the olde man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth by hys baptiſyng in his age no more then a chylde deſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth by his baptime receiued in his infancy. Furthermore: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the promiſſe of ſaluation per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyneth as wel vnto childeren, as to men, and wemen: it muſt nedes folowe, that the ſygne of the promys belongeth as well vnto childer, as to olde folke.</p>
            <p>But baptime is the ſygne, or ſacrament of the promiſſe, that GOD made to vs of the newe Teſtament: therefore baptyme belongeth as wel vnto chylde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, as vnto olde folke. If that ye denye, that the promyſſe of ſaluation perteyneth as well vnto chylder, as to olde folke
<pb facs="tcp:1922:50"/> (as ye dydde ones in my cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, reaſonynge wyth me) I wyll proue it thus: ſaluation belongeth as well vnto chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as to men, and wemen: and no man commeth vnto the herytage of ſaluacion, but thorow the promys: as Paule witneſſeth. Gala. ij. <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Si ex lege eſt he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditas, non iam expromiſſione. Atqui Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hae per promiſſionem donauit deus.</hi>
               </q> If that the heritage, that is the kyngdome of heauen commeth thorow the lawe, then it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not of the promys. But GOD gaue it vnto Abraham by the promys. And ſo all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bothe Abrahams poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytye, and they that are of the Heathen receyue the heritage, as Abraham dyd. Then when as the herytage commeth by the promys: none can haue the
<pb facs="tcp:1922:50"/> heretage, that hathe not the promys: but the ſpecheles chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der haue the heretage, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they haue alſo the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys of the heretage. If that chylder haue the promys, and the couenant, and the thynge promyſed by the couenaunt: why maye not they haue the ſygne, or ſeale of the couenant as well as the infantes of the Iewes hadde the ſygne and ſeale of theyr couenant: Is the Baptyme of water grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then the thynge whyche is ſygnifyed by the Baptyme: is the garland of Iuy better, then the Wine, whyche is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifyed by the garlande? When as childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receiue the holy goſte the heretage of the kingdom of heauen, forgeuenes of origenal
<pb facs="tcp:1922:51"/> ſinne by Chriſtes blode, and are made membres of Chriſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: why may they not receyue the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of baptim, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is an holy ſygne and ſeale of theſe thynges? maye we not receiue the leſſe, when we haue receiued the greater? yf that ye deny the kingdome of heauen, and the heretage therof to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine vnto childer (as for to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme your opinion ye wold not ſtik to do) for ye deny as greate a'thynge as that: I wyll proue that the heretage doth pertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne unto them. Iacob, Hieremi, and Iohan the Baptiſt, beynge chylder hadde the heretage of the kyngdome of heauen: and the chylder both of the Iewes and alſo of the chylder of the Chriſtianes haue the promys of the heretage, as theſe places
<pb facs="tcp:1922:51"/> folowynge do teſtyfie. I wyll make ſtronge my cumnant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene me and the, and thy ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de after the, in their generaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in a continuall comnant: that is to wyt, that I wyll be a GOD vnto the and to thy ſede after the. And agayne in the .xxij. of Geneſis. In thy ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſhall all the nacions of the earth be bliſſed. In the .xliiij. of Eſaye is thys prymis. I wyll poure oute my Spirite vpon thy ſede, and my bleſſyng vpon thy buddes. And Peter in the ſecond of the Actes ſpeketh of a playn promis in theſe wordes The promys was made vnto you, and to youre chylder, and to all that are far of, whome ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the Lorde oure GOD ſhall call. Lo, here is playne mention made, of the promys
<pb facs="tcp:1922:52"/> made vnto chylder. Then when as GOD perfourmeth all that he promyſeth: and he promyſed ſaluation vnto chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, it foloweth, that they haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heretage that GOD promyſed them, then doth the heretage and kyngdome of GOD perteyne vnto them. Why do you ſo vncharitably wyth hold the ſygne and ſeale of ſaluation from chylderen, to whome the heretage belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth? Who gaue you any ſuch authoritie, ye proude and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous tyrannes: as to make wardes of the chylder of GOD, and to wyth hold from them the ſygne and ſeale of theyr fathers heretage. Now where is all your ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: whyche ye booſt that ye defende youre errour wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all?
<pb facs="tcp:1922:52"/> aunſwere vnto theſe ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and confute them, yf ye can. Where as ye ſaye after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, that nother the ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of Chryſtes Supper, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the raynbowe ſygnyfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth anye thynge to chylder: ye are farre oute of the waye. The breakynge of the breade in the ſupper, and deliuerynge of it vnto the congregation be tokeneth: that Chriſtes body was broken for all them that ſhal be ſaued: and that the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his paſſion ſhulde be delt to all them that are elect, and choſen to be ſaued. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when as childer are elect and choſen to be ſaued, is the miſterye of Chriſtes ſupper, no ſigne of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation vnto childer. Doth not the rayne bow ſignifie to al the worlde, that the world ſhal no
<pb facs="tcp:1922:53"/> more be drowned wyth water. Doth not that promis, that the worlde ſhuld be no more deſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed wyth water, perteyne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to chylder? If that the promys perteyne vnto childeren: how happeneth, that the ſigne of the promys ſignifieth nothyng vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them? It muſt nedes ſignify vnto yong childer, as well as to olde men, that they ſhall not be drowned wyth an vniuerſall ſloude, as the worlde was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes deſtroyed. So dothe the baptyſynge of chylderen ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, as well vnto chylder: that Chriſt dyed for them, and ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe for them, as it ſygnifyeth the ſame to olde menne. For all althoughe they ſee not the ſygne and knowe not of the ſygne: yet maye they haue it as ſurely, as thei haue the thing
<pb facs="tcp:1922:53"/> ſygnyfyed by the ſygne.</p>
            <p>Almyghtie GOD made a couenaunt and promyſſe, not onely vnto menne, but alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to byrdes and beſtes: that they ſhuld not be drowned with the vniuerſall fould. Geneſis .ix. Beholde (ſayth the Lorde) I make my couenaunt wyth you and wyth yourſede after you, and wyth euery lyuynge ſoule that is wyth you, as well foul, as cattell and beeſtes. Thys ſhall be the ſygne, whyche I geue betwene you and me and euery lyuynge ſoule why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is wyth you. I haue ſet my bowe in the cloude: and it ſhall be a ſygne a ſygne of the couenaunt betwene me and the yearthe. So, that when I bryng cloudes vpon the yearth the bowe ſhall appeare in the
<pb facs="tcp:1922:54"/> cloudes: and then wyll I thynk vpon the comnant betwene me and you, and all lyuyng crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>Fyrſte I gather of thys pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce that the comnant of GOD is profytable, not onely vnto them that haue the vſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but alſo vnto byrdes and vnreaſonable beſtes, although they knowe, nothynge at all of the promys. I gather alſo, that the ſygnes of Goddes comnaunte, are ſygnes vnto byrdes and beeſtes: and not onely ſygnes, but profytable ſygnes vnto them: althou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe they neuer ſee them, nor vnderſtande theim. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I gather that the holy ſygne of Baptyme, is not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely a ſigne vnto childer of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb facs="tcp:1922:54"/> of ſynnes, and of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des fauor toward them, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a fruitful &amp; profitable ſigne. For how can the ſygne of the raynbow be more profytable vnto vnreſonable beaſtes, and byrdes, then the Sacramte of baptyme is profytable vnto yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g chylder? ſeyng that GOD promyſed as well ſaluation to chylder, from hell, death, and damnation, and made baptyme the ſygne thereof, as he promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto beaſtes and byrdes ſafe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garde from general drowning, and made the raynbow the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſygne or ſeal of the ſame. Here is your ſayinge, that the raynebowe is noo ſygne vnto chyldern, proued playne falſe, and contrarye vnto the open text of Goddes holy word.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1922:55"/>
            <p>Where is the great clerke that, ſayde, that I ſhould not haue Wincheſter in hande, when I had hym in hande? as thoughe he had paſſed Wyncheſter ſo far in wyt and learnyng, that ther were no compariſon to be made betwene them. Here myght ye be aſhamed, yf ye hadde anyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhame at all. Here myght your diſciples be aſhamed of ſuche an vnlearned and dotynge ſcole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter. Is the ſeale of a childes landes no ſeale vnto hym: becau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe he hath no knowlege of the ſeale, and knoweth nothynge therof? What ſoeuer ye aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, the ſeale is euen a ſeale vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to chylder: and when they come to age, they clayme theyr lands therby. Euen ſo is baptyme a ſeal of remiſſion of ſynnes vnto chyldern, although they know
<pb facs="tcp:1922:55"/> it not. And when they cum to age, it ſhal be an aſſurance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, to clayme the promiſſ of God by: ye haue been therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to bolde to bable of theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters: where in ye haue very lyttelle ſkill, And pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce as boldelye, as though ye were ſyttynge vpon Apolloes treſtell. Let youre I ſayes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue autorite amonge your bewit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched ſcholars, as much as ye wyll: but they ſhal haue none with me, excepte ye can proue your ſaying true by the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. Ye axe me, why is baptym not differred, as wel as the ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per of the Lorde? A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might anſwer you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wer lyke to be lurched at your gluttenous ſupper, yf that they were with you: for ye wolde haue at the ſupper of the gluttenous cataba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptiſtes
<pb facs="tcp:1922:56"/> (whiche ye call the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of oure Lord) befe, mutton, vele, capons and ſuch harde meates, as the pore ſucking chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der can not eat: and therfore it were no wiſdom that thei ſhuld ſuppe with you, vntyl theyr teeth wer growen. If that I had bylded my opynion vpon doctores, and ſtories, as ye do yours. I coulde haue broughte manye places both oute of the doctours, and ſtories: which proue that it was the cuſtome a .M.CC. yeres ago, to gyue the Sacramente of CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STES body and blud, only in bred and wyne, vnto the yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g chylder ſtreyght waye after ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptyme. But becauſe I ground my opinion only vpon ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, I wyll aunſwere you by ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. The ſupper of the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:1922:56"/> requireth a doer, and it is an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Sacramente, For Chriſt ſayeth.
<q>
                  <hi>Accipite, edite, bibite, facite in mei recorda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem.</hi>
               </q> Take ye, eate ye, drinke ye, and do ye thys in the remembrance of me. Then when as the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der can not receyue the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and can not eat, drynk, nor do that in the ſupper that God requireth, that is to eat, &amp; drink in the remembraunce of hym: it is mete that chylder be dyffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the ſupper vntyl they may, and can eat and drynk and receyue the ſupper, as Chriſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened it to be receyued. And be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe baptim is a paſſiue Sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, &amp; no man can baptiſe hym ſelf, but is baptiſe do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an other: &amp; childer may be as wel dipped in to the water in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:1922:57"/> (which is the outward baptym and as myche as one man can gyue an other) euen as olde fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke: and when as they haue the promiſſe of ſaluation, as well as old folk, &amp; can receyue the ſigne of the ſame as wel: there is no cauſe why that the baptyme of chylder ſhulde be differed. CHRIST dyd not baptyſe hymſelf, but Iohan the baptiſt baptiſed hym. In the ſecond of the actes and the .x. where as manye were baptiſed, no man baptyſed hym felf: nother do we rede in any place of the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament: that any man baptiſed hym ſelf, then when as baptym is gyuen by other: and the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lorde is taken of a man by hym ſelf: it foloeth not that baptym ought to be differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſo longe, as the ſupper
<pb facs="tcp:1922:57"/> ought to be differed, Wee reade in the actes of he Apoſtels, that all they that came into the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhyppe of Chriſtes churche, entred in by baptym, and dyd not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate ſtreighte waye after they were baptiſed. All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I grant with in a ſhorte tyme after, they receyued the ſupper of the Lorde, as many as were able to receuer it. Then when as chylder perteyne vnto chriſtes churche, it is mete that they entre in by the ſame dore, that olde folke enter in by: then oughte they not to be holden out from the churche, vntyll they may allſo receiue CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STES ſupper. Baptym is the putting on of CHRIST, as Paule ſayeth.
<q>
                  <hi>Quotquot baptizati estis, Christum induistis.</hi>
               </q> As many of you as ar baptiſed,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:58"/> haue CHRIST put vpon you, Is it conuentent that the pore infantes ſhalbe naked, and want CHRIST vnput vpon them, vntyll that they come to the .xiiij. yeare of theyr age? Howe ſhall they come worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to Chriſtes ſupper, and haue not CHRIST for they gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? Therefore they muſt fyrſt put on Chriſte by baptyme, and then afterward at conuenient tyme, receyue the Lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, I ſhewed that water pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſed vnclenes in all that ar baptyſed: and I ſet the ſygne of the water, as an argumente agaynſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your ſect, which deny originall ſyn. But ye ſaye, that I haue proued nether of both, vnleſſe I proue that Chriſt ordeded that chylder ſhulde be baptiſed. To proue that the wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:1922:58"/> in baptyme, ſignifyeth the impurite of them that are Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptyſed. Ananias ſayde vnde Peter,
<q>
                  <hi>Exurge, &amp; baptizare, &amp; ablue peccata tua.</hi>
               </q> Ryſe vp and be baptyſed and waſhe away thy ſynnes, ſaynt Paul calleth baptym the bathe of regeneration and the bath of water, wherby the churche is made clene. In all thes places ye hear mention of waſſhynge and water, and of ſcouryng by the water, wherfore that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of baptyſme ſignifyeth that they that are baptyſed, haue nede of waſhynge, and are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clene, yf they be chyldern, and haue committed no actuall ſyn, then it folowethe, that they are defyled with originall ſyn yf they be commede vnto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyt age, that then they ar ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:1922:59"/> both with originall and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſynne. The former part is proued. The other parte I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue thus. Baptym ſignifieth in all them that are baptyſed, that they are vnclene, and haue ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſyn, but chyldern are bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſed, therfore the water ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in theyr baptym, that they are gyltye of original ſyn, ſeyng that they haue commytted no actuall as yet. If ye ſaye that chyldern are vnworthlly bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſed, therfore the water of theyr Baptyme, condemneth them not of originall ſynne, and wanteth the ſygnyfication, I anſwer that the vnworthynes of the receyuynge of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente, hyndereth not the ſygnification of it, allthought it be both vnprofytable, and alſo damnable to the receauer,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:59"/> of vnworthelye. When as a noughtye mane receyueth the Sacramente of CHRIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TES bodye vnworthelye, doth the brekinge of the bread leue of ſygnifying that CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STES body was broken for that ſynfull and vnworthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuer? Therfore baptym in all that ar baptyſed, betokeneth that they are gyltyl of originall ſyn at the leaſte. Where as ye ſaye, that for lack of ſcripture I am faine to flye vnto rryginall ſyn to proue the baptym of chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dern: I praye you what ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re haue ye broughte, ſence the beginninge of your boke, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the contrary? Whether I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue broughte any ſcripture for the probation of my opynion, or no I reporte me vnto the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of my ſermon, and of thys
<pb facs="tcp:1922:60"/> booke alſo. Where as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement is generall, and perteyneth vnto an hole ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all kynd it perteyneth to euery one, conteyned vnder the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall kynde, althoughe the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular be not expreſſedly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as in thys example, if that all men be reſonable lyuynge creatures, then chylder are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo reſonable creatures: becauſe they are conteyned vnder the name of a man, thoughe they are not expreſſed by name in the generall. Or els yf that were not true, howe ſhoulde ye proue, that wemen, ſhoulde be ſaued: that wyues, wydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, and maydens ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the Lordes ſupper and be baptyſed: ſeynge that the apoſtels haue no expreſſed com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement of GOD, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:1922:60"/> the women ſhulde be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſed nother be receyued vnto the ſupper of the Lorde. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore excepte ye wil exclude and ſhyt out wemen from the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lorde, and from bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tim, becauſe there is no expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed word to commaunde them to be baptiſed, and to receyue Chriſtus ſupper: ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſhyt out ceylder from baptime. For chylder are as well conteyned vnder thys worde nations: as wemen bee, in thys generall precepte, teache all nations, and baptyſe them into the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the father and the ſonne, and the holy ghoſte. If that ye aunſwere, that preachyng and Baptyſynge be tyed together, and they oughte alwayes to bee doone together. I reade that Chryſte ſayde vnto hys
<pb facs="tcp:1922:61"/> Apoſtels. Mar. xvi. preache ye the Goſpel vnto euery creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. If thys worde creature do ſignifie here man: then are the Apoſtels (when as baptime is vnſeperably ioyned with prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge) bounde to baptiſe all that they preache to: and they are bounde to preache to all men, therefore by youre reaſon they are bounde to baptiſe all men. Chylder are men, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtels are bound to baptiſe chylder and to preache vnto chylder. If that ye ſaye that preache the Goſpell, vnto all menne, is to be thus vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande: preache the Goſpel vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all men that can receyue the preachyng: then is the lyke ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall precept, baptiſe all men ſo to be vnderſtande: that they are to be baptiſed, whyche can
<pb facs="tcp:1922:61"/> receyue baptime. But the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Chriſtians canne as well receiue the ouer baptime whiche is the dippyng into the water in the name of Chriſte. as the infantes of the Iewes could receyue the ſacrament of circumciſion: Then are childer as well to be baptiſed, as olde folke are to be preached vnto, and to be baptiſed. Ar we now ſo deſtitute of ſcripture, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue that infantes maye be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſed, that we are fayne to fly for helpe to original ſinne? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as I proue by that, that chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der haue originall ſynne, that they hadde nede of the bath of water and regeneration: do I flye from ſcrypture? is the matter of origynall ſynne no part of ſcripture? you do holde that there is none at all, and
<pb facs="tcp:1922:62"/> therefore that the childer nede not, nother ought to be bapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, vntyll they be .xiiij. yeare olde: before whiche tyme, they haue done many actuall ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whyche hadde nede to be waſſhed awaye, wyth the bath of baptime. Therefore it is no meruell that ye exclude origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſynne from ſcripture, as a thing whiche can not be found in ſcripture.</p>
            <p>In youre nexte queſtion, ye make as wiſe a reaſon, agaynſt me: as ye dyd in the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of youre booke, dyuerſe times. This is my reaſon, that ye go aboute to confute and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe.</p>
            <p>As for the vſe of water is, to clenge and ſcoure thynges that are vncleane, and ſygni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth where it is brought that
<pb facs="tcp:1922:62"/> there is ſome thynge, whyche nedeth to be made clene, ſo in oure baptyme the water doth ſignifye vnto vs, that there is ſome vnclennes and fylthynes in our nature, that had nede to be waſhed. For thys cauſe I may ſett the water in our bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tym for an argument agaynſt them, that ſay that men as ſoone as they be borne, haue no origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſynne. But let vs ſe your ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gument agaynſt thys my ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<q>☞ Is that a ſuffycyent cauſe to proue orygynall ſynn to be in infantes, becauſe ye offer them water?</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ I aunſwer, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptim of infan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes being lawfull, &amp; godly, as I do preſuppoſe it: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water of baptim (which vnfaithfullye ye cal onli water, leuing out of bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tim) muſt nedes ſignifi vnto chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:1922:63"/> that they are vnclene. But when as they haue committed no actuall ſynne, and are yet ſynnes: it foloweth, that they haue origynall ſynne: excepte there be mo ſynnes, then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and originall. But nowe let vs heare youre hole argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherewith ye intende to boxe me.
<q>Is that a ſufficient cauſe, to proue ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſynne to be in infantes becauſe ye offer them water? Then is it as ſufficient to proue that the Turkes and Iewes, wyth al the reſt of the people of the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de haue it not, nor are infected therewyth becauſe ye offer it not vnto them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I aunſwere vnto thys argu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, by ſhewyng the like: how ſtronge, and myghtye thys of yours is. Preachyng of Gods
<pb facs="tcp:1922:63"/> worde preſuppoſeth, that ther, where it is preached, men are in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fected with originall and actual ſynne. but ye offer no preaching of Gods word, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, Turkes, and vnto the reſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infydeles in the world: therfore ye recken, that nether Turke, nor Iew, nether any other infy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dele hath, ether originall, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſynne. If that ye thynke, that all the aboue reherſed infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deles haue both originall, and actuall ſynne. for all that ye of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them no preachynge: ſo I thynke, that the forſayd infyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les haue orygynall ſynne, not withſtandyng, that I offer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no water. In your next reaſon, ye preſuppoſe it, that I dyd ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beleue, ſence I hadde anye knowledge in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture: that is, that the water of baptyme ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:1922:64"/> awaye the vnclennes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule: but well wot I, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſte worketh onelye that worke, and no creature in the worlde, I knowe, that Chriſtes hole baptyme, that is, both the outwarde, and the inner toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, purgeth both bodye, and ſoule. And I do fynd in dyuerſe places of the newe Teſtament: that it hath pleaſed GOD, to graunt forgyueneſſe of ſynnes, by the inwarde baptyme, when the outward baptyme was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, that the thyng ſignyfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhulde agree wyth the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſigne, and ſygnyfyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon.</p>
            <p>Peter ſayd in the ſecond chap. of the actes. Let euery one of you be baptyſed in the name of Ieſu Chriſte, to the forgyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſynne: and ye ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue
<pb facs="tcp:1922:64"/> the gyft of the holy ghoſt. Peter alſo ſayeth. Acto. x.</p>
            <p>What lette is there, that theſe be not baptyſed in water, whyche haue receyued the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſte, as well as we? And Luke telleth, that the meany of Cornelius receyued the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſte, and were contynentie baptyſed with water. Ananias alſo, in the .ix. of the actes, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto Paule. Brother Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, the lorde, whom thou ſaweſt, in the way, hath ſente me: that thou ſhouldeſt receyue thy ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght agayne, and be fylled wyth the holy ghoſte, and immedia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telye, there fell from hys eyes, as they had bene ſcales: and he receyued hys ſyghte, and roſe, &amp; was baptyſed, ye ſe now, how that God ioyneth in hys word the two baptymes together: ſo
<pb facs="tcp:1922:65"/> that the outwarde baptyme is not a vayne ſigne, and to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſed: as ye ſeme to do: where as ye axe: how can water hele the woundes of the ſoul. But leaſte ye ſaye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I alledge your mynde falſely, I wyll rehearſe your wordes, as ye wrote the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<q>☞ But nowe I ſaye, that all the worlde hath ſynned, and is defyled in Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Howe nowe, wyll water ſcoure awaye the fylthe of thps corruptyon? No. It is a wounde, receiued in the ſoule, and is waſhed away, but wyth the only fayth in the bloude of Chriſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Ye ſay here, that all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world hath ſynned, and is defyled in Adam. and yf ye meane no ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tylte, and vnderſtande by the worlde, both the electe and the other lykewyſe: ye graunte o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly orygynalle ſynne, whych
<pb facs="tcp:1922:65"/> in other places ye haue denied, and do denye: as hereafter we ſhall proue, both by your ſaying and doynge. If that all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world hath ſynned in Adam: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue alſo yonge chyldren ſynned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. and ye ſaye, that the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Adam can not be ſcou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red awaye wyth anye thynge, ſauyng only wyth the fayth in the bloud of Chriſte. Ye ſaye alſo, that no chylde hath fayth: and therfore call all infantes, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beleuers. It foloweth of youre ſayenge: that ye are of that opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyon, that all the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which dyed, ſence the begynnynge of the worlde, vnto thys daye, dyed vnpurged from the fylth of the ſoule, and wythout for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyuenes of origynall ſynne. Whoſe rewarde, ſeynge that it is the death of the ſoule, and
<pb facs="tcp:1922:66"/> euerlaſtynge dampnatyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it maye be gathered, that ye are of thys opynyon, that all chylderen are in the ſtate of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natyon: and that, yf they dye, they are all dampned. For thys argument maye be clearelye, and truely gathered of youre owne ſayinge.</p>
            <p>¶ None ſhall be ſcoured fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the corruption of orygynall ſynne, but ſuche as haue fayth in the bloude of Chriſte. But all chylderne wante fayth in the bloude of Chriſte: as ye teache both openlye, and pryuelye. Therfore by you, no chylderne are ſcoured from the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of orygynall ſynne.</p>
            <p>¶ Wherevpon it foloweth: yf theſe ſayinges of Paule be true: Euyll was broughte by
<pb facs="tcp:1922:66"/> lynage into all men, by the tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſſe of one man, vnto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnatyon: The rewarde of ſynne, is death: By Adam all men do dye, and by one manne, ſynne entred into the worlde, and thorough ſynne, death, as farre furth as we haue all ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: that all chyldern (whych as ye holde, are vnbeleuers, and therefore can not be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for lacke of fayth in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bloude) muſte nedes be damned. Whych opinion, howe wycked it is, and howe contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye vnto the holye ſcrypture: lette the chyrch of <hi>CHRIST</hi> gyue ſentence. Haue ye not taught holſome leſſons in youre boke, wherof ſuche a damnable concluſyon foloweth? Are ye not worthye to be dubbed a doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tour of hereſye? If ye be not
<pb facs="tcp:1922:67"/> I can not tell, who is. Wher as ye ſay: that water ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſcoure the ſoule. becauſe orygynall ſyn is a wounde receyued of the ſoule: ye ſeme to mene, that the bodye ſhall not be damned for orygynall ſynne, as a thing that neuer receyued it.</p>
            <p>Is it not agaynſt iuſtyce, that they ſhoulde be condemned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, whych were not conioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned in the dede doynge, that de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerued damnation?</p>
            <p>¶ Ye holde in youre nexte ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence a maruelous opynyon: whyche is thys.
<q>It is to be vnderſtande, that thoughe ſynne be common to all, yet baptyme is not common to all.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Whych ſentence ſemeth not to be true. For to whomſoeuer preaching is common, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame is alſo baptyme common.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1922:67"/>
            <p>For preachyng, and baptyſyng are ioyned, and commaunded together, in theſe wordes.
<q>
                  <hi>Euntes docete omnes gentes, baptizantes eas.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Go, and teache all natyons, baptyſyng them. Then is bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme, as common as preaching is: hut preachyng is common to all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therfore is alſo baptyme common to all: though all wyll not receyue it. For a man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge ſeuerall grounde ynough of hys owne, oft tymes putteth no cattell into the comon: all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hys parte is as commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto hym, as vnto anye other man. Are the feldes no more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vnto a man, after that he enioyeth no longer the profyte of the common feldes? Anſwer me wyth ſcrypture, as I do confute yow wyth ſcrypture: and let your arrogant, I ſays,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:68"/> (whyche ye haue wythin thre leues of the begynnyng of your booke in the ſtede of ſcrypture boldly brought in thre tymes) goo, ſhake theyr eares. For thoughe ye haue inchaunted your wretched ſcholars, ſo that they beleue, that it is the goſpel, whatſoeuer ye ſay: yet are ye in no ſuch autoryte, maiſter doctor with me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wyll beleue your, I ſay: when as ye bryng neuer one text of ſcrypture, to bylde your I ſay, vpon. Well I deny the doctor, ſaye what he wyll: and ſet theſe textes of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture agaynſt hym: Paule wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vnto the Romanes thus. As by the treſpas of one man, euel was brought by lynage in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all men to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation: ſo by the rightuouſnes of one, good came vnto all men, to the iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation
<pb facs="tcp:1922:68"/> of lyfe? Then is iuſtifyca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion as comon, as condemnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: And baptym is as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon as iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifycatyon is: then is baptyme common vnto as many as ſinne is common to. Saynt Ihon ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeth, that Chriſt obteyned mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye for our ſynnes. and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for our ſynnes, but for the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of the hole worlde. Lo here is mercy and remyſſyon of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as generall, and as commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as ſynne is. And baptyme is common to all, to whome remiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon of ſynne is common: for baptym: is the ſeale of forgyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſynnes: and ſo he that ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth the one common, maketh alſo the other common. youre meruelous ſentence therefore, will not ſtand with ſcripture. Of lyke folyſhnes is youre con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſyon, that foloweth: that is,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:69" rendition="simple:additions"/> that baptyme is to be offered to all men: yet is it not to be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to all men, nor to be taken of all men. Whoſoeuer offereth anye thynge to anye creature, and intendeth not to gyue the ſame, mocketh the creature: as when the Popiſhe prieſt, ſayeth vnto hys pariſhoners, <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>Accipite, &amp; comedite,</hi>
               </q> take ye, and eate ye: and gyueth them nothyng, but ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all hym ſelfe: mocketh hys pariſhoners. And ye captaynes of catabaptiſtrye, offer baptyme vnto all chyldren, and intend not to gyue it vnto them.</p>
            <p>Therfore ye mocke all chylderne: lyke as boyes mock yong byrdes, and yong chou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghes: whyles ye offer vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> baptyme, whych ye neuer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende to gyue them.</p>
            <p>¶ For the confutacyon of
<pb facs="tcp:1922:69"/> the laſte parte of your ſayinge: that is, that baptyme is not to be taken of all men: I aſke you, whether mortification, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generacyon ought to be taken of all men, or no? If that morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatyon, and regeneratyon ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to be receyued of all men: and true baptym is true morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycation and perfyt regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon: then ought all men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue baptym. That baptim is mortyfycacyon, and regeneraci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on: Paule beareth witnes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romanes in the ſixt Chapter: and vnto Titus, the thyrd chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter: and in other places, whych I might here reherſe, if I thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght not theſe ſufficient. And ſo is your ſayng falſe, that all men ought not to the baptyſed. But what if all men ought not to be baptiſed? What hindereth that
<pb facs="tcp:1922:70"/> baptiſyng of yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? What if many wicked perſones be not worthy, to receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeal of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I mean y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward baptime: becauſe thei wilfulli, &amp; willingly refuſe mortification, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God: ſhal their vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> innocent childer, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt hath waſſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his bloud, vnmet &amp; vnworthy, to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeal of the promis which god made vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſayng of yours, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght not to receiue bapti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, proueth nothing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chylder ought not to be baptized. here may al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſe: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your ground y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye wold make, is but ſande, &amp; falleth, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is but lightly touched, &amp; that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye wold bylde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your funda<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can fynd no faſt grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to reſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherfore ye ar not lyke to proſper in your purpoſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1922:70"/>
            <p>baptim, ſay ye, is onli dew to the elect churche, choſen in Chriſte Ieſus, before al worldes: What maketh this agaynſt the chriſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning of yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g childer? I tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k yow for ye help me with argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, agaynſte your falſe doctrine. For if baptim be only dew vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elect churche, choſen in Chriſt Ieſus before al worldes: then is baptim dew vnto al the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres, &amp; ſparkes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame churche: but chylder ar membres, &amp; a part of the elect churche. Therfore bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tim is dew vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. What nede vs now to diſpute any longer in this matter, ſeyng that by your own ſaye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, baptim is dew vnto childer, as the membres of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes elect churche, choſen befor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worldes? Is baptim only dew to the elect and choſen? if that be ſo: your brether anabaptiſtes of munſter did wrong, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they
<pb facs="tcp:1922:71"/> baptyſed ſo many deuiliſhe and reprobat perſones of your ſect: that they by theyr myght and ſtrenght, put down all lawfull magiſtrates, and rulers there, and ſet vp a Kyng among them ſelues: which had .xvi. wyues, were theſe murderers and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſers of goddis miniſters, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elect chyrche? was thys kyng ryghtly regenerate, and a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifyer of hys membres vpon earth, which had ſo many wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to exercyſe hys fleſhly luſt vpon? were not your rebapty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing brethern, which were ſlaye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Amſterda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they thought to haue murdered the magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and gouernores of the cyti reprobate and of a falſly preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and fayned repentaunce? And yet ye ſaye: that baptyme ought only to be geuen vnto
<pb facs="tcp:1922:71"/> ſuche, as vnfeynedly wyll ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d theyr lyues, whereby ye make a concluſion, that chylder ought not to be baptyſed: becauſe ye cannot perceyue, whether chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der entend vnfaynedly to ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d theyr lyues, or no: &amp; know not by theyr lyuyng, whether they be choſen, or vnchoſen. Thys is one of the chefe argumentes, wher wyth ye go about to ouer throw the baptyſyng of chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: whiche is after ſuche a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner formed: that it taketh as wel away the baptim of old folk as of chylder, for if that ye wyll baptyſe none but ſuche as, ye know whether they be elected, and vnfaynedly repent or no: ye ſhal as well holde al olde folk from baptym as yong chylder, for no man can know the harte, nether of olde ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor childe, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng
<pb facs="tcp:1922:72"/> only God, as it is wryte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ij. Pararipo. vi.
<q>
                  <hi>Tu ſolus nosti cor filiorum hominum.</hi>
               </q> Thou knoweſt onli the harte of the ſonnes of men then may all they that ar baptyſed feyn and counterfet repentance &amp; amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of lyfe before the elders which baptiſe, and intend no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng leſſ as Symon Magus and Iudas Dyd in the Apoſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les tymes, &amp; in our tymes ſuche ſwarmes of Anabaptiſtes of your ſect, whiche were baptiſed after the .xiiij. yeare of ther age, and afterwarde committed hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom robry and ſhamefull mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the aboue reherſed cities: and yit was noman able, ſauing only god, to iuge whether they were choſen or vnchoſen: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d theyr lyuyng or no, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of theyr
<pb facs="tcp:1922:72"/> Baptime. Ye ſay that infantes ought not to be baptiſed becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not tel whether they be of the elect chyrche or no, and whether they ar fully amynded to ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d theyr lyuing or no. Ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke yow .iiij. men of .xl. yeares of age to baptiſe, &amp; let me take .iiij. infantes of .iiij. dayes olde: tell me how that ye know that your iiij. men of .xl. yeares, ar more elect and choſen then I know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the .iiij. children ar elect &amp; cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen: ſeing that the ſcripture is playn, that no man can tel, what an other man inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth or what is in hys harte. Then when as acordyng vnto the ſayng of S. Paul .i. Corint. ij. No man kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the thynges whyche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyn vnto man ſauyng the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of man whych is in hym: no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can tel whether an oldeman
<pb facs="tcp:1922:73"/> be more electe then a chylde, then if olde men ought to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſed, not with ſtandyng that noman knoweth whether they be worthy loue or hatred, and be choſen or vnchoſen, it ſhal not hyndre but that chyldern may be as wel baptiſed as olde folke, ye ſay in your next aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that,
<q>Remiſſion of ſin is offered to all: but al receyue it not.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ I wyll now try your ſpirit whether it is ſtedfaſt or vnſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt and wauering or no, ye ſayd a litle before that.
<q>Baptym is offered euen to as many, as wyll vnfayneoly amend theyr lyues: euen as is remiſſion of ſynnes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ In which place ye make bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tym and remiſſion of ſynnes all alyke como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but remiſſion of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is comon to all men, both to &amp; olde meton chylder: and that
<pb facs="tcp:1922:73"/> I proue by your owne ſayng, whych is that remiſſion of ſyn is offered to all. For it that is offered to all, is como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all: ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore by your own ſayng it fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth that baptime is comon to all. And if it be comon to all, then is it comon vnto chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. How doth now youre ſpirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre with it ſelf, that ſayd a litle before: that baptim was not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to al: &amp; now ſaith it the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it foloweth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily, that baptim is comon to al. How do theſe ſaynges of yours agree together: remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of finnes is offered only vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that wyll vnfaynedly amende theyr lyues, as baptim is offered: and remiſſion of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is offered to all, but all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue it not. In the one place ye offer remiſſion of ſynne on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:1922:74"/> vnto them theat baptim is to be offered to, that is to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wil repent: and in the other vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all, Is not here a prety argu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment? thys is the ſpirit whiche ye receiued in the wood, wher as ye tolde me that ye learned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any doctor your diuinite.</p>
            <p>I gather alſo of this your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, where ye ſaie, that remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſyn is offered to all, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſin is alſo offred vnto childer: and to whom ſoeuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſyon of ſyn perteineth, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time alſo perteyneth, as it may be plainly gathered of youre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wn wordes aboue reherſed: but remiſſion of ſyn is comon to all: therfore is alſo baytym comon vnto al: why ſhulde not he haue the ſigne which hath the thing. Now is your ſaing that baptim is not como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto al, onis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futed
<pb facs="tcp:1922:74"/> againe. This do I aſke you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye ſay that remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſyn is offered vnto al: whether re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſynne is offered vnto any, ſauyng vnto them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue: and whether beleeſe cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth only of the hearing of god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des worde or no. If that forgy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenes of ſyns only be to be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to them that haue faith, and ſaith be only offered vnto them that heare the word: how haue the Turkes and the other infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deles remiſſion of ſynnes offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto them, when as they want the word of God wher of cummeth fayth, whiche only as ye graunt, the promys of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſynnes? Then muſte ye ſhew in your aunſwere, how that remiſſion of ſynnes is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to the faythles and vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuynge Turkes, whych wane
<pb facs="tcp:1922:75"/> the inſtrument whereby fayth is offred and ingendred. This do I only wryte to put you to youre proue: ye are ſo full of youre generall concluſyones, if that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church ſanctified in the word of Chriſt by faith only re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue remiſſion of ſinnes (as ye write here in thys place) &amp; if it be trew that ye did hold before that childer are faythles &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleuing: it foloweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chylder receiue no remiſſion of ſynnes, by your ſaing: is not this to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne all childer, or els to ſay, that childer haue no originall ſyn? whether this be holſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine or no, let Chriſtes church be iuge. As for your argument that ye bring next here after I deny the antecede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, if ye meane of ſuch faith as ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> declare it ſelf by good workes: for the childer
<pb facs="tcp:1922:75"/> obtein remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynnes by the blood of Chriſt: althouge they haue no ſuch faith as you do re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quire in them: your argument is thys.
<q>Thys I ſay <hi>
                     <hi>(wher is now)</hi> Hec dicit dominus)</hi> the remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynnes is offered to all: but all receyue it not the: churche ſanctiſyed by faith in the blood of Chriſt only receiueth it: and vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time belongeth: therefore none ought to receiue it but ſuch as haue not only heard the good promiſes of God: but haue alſo thereby receyued a ſyngular conſolation in their hartes through remiſſion of ſynne whiche they by fayth haue receyued: For yf any receiue baptim without theis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion, it profiteth hym nothyng.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I haue proued ſuffyciently before that the Iewes circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was theſame, &amp; of theſame effect &amp; ſtrength with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that baptime is to vs. But the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:1922:76"/> of the Iewes hauynge, no more fayth then oure children, and being no more ſanctified by faith in the blood of Chriſt then ours be, and haue receyued no more conſolation of Goddes promiſſes then our children ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue done: obteyned forgyuenes of ſynnes and haue taken wyth fruite the ſygne and ſeale of the ſame, I mean their circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherevpon I gather yf: that the Iewes childer, were wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith, and were only ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the promis and mercy of god, and not by theyr own faith or any thing of their owndoing and wer not withſtanding law fully receiued in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> felouſhip of the faithful church by circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and obteined forgiuenes of ſinnes: then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as God regar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth nomore a Iew then a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:76"/> and hath promiſed as wel to be a god to the childer of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuyng Gentils, as of the bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng Iewes: the childer of the faythful Chriſtians receiue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſynnes by the promis and mercy of god, before the vſe and exerciſe of faith, and are as lawfully receyued by baptim in to the felowſhip and the chuche of the ſaithful chriſtians, and to the partaking of forgyuenes of ſynnes, as the Iewes chylder were receiued in to the Iewes churche, and were made parte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners by circumciſion of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys and forgiuenes of ſynnes. Now muſt ye ether deny y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god is ſo good vnto the chryſtyans childer as he was vnto the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes childer, or els that our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der haue remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes, &amp; ar as lawfully baptiſed, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iewes
<pb facs="tcp:1922:77"/> childer were circumciſed: not withſtanding that our childer be not as yet for lack of age, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to the vſe and exercyſe of faith. Ye hold &amp; repete in thys your reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an opinion &amp; a falſe hereſy againſt the ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcriptur.
<q>That Sacramentes do not profit them whiche heare not the promys, and knowe not what it meaneth.</q>
            </p>
            <p>For the confutacion of thys I aſke you whether the Iewes childer, which nether heard the promis made vnto Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther receiued any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation by it, ſhuld haue ben ſaued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hell and da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation if thei had depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted two daies after their circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or they ſhuld haue not ben damned: &amp; if that any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had died vpon the .x. daye with out circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: whether thei ſhuld haue ben da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned or ſaued? If ye
<pb facs="tcp:1922:77"/> anſwer with the ſcriptur y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not withſtanding that they knewe not the promis nether heard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time of it, that (God which ſaid, I wil be thy god &amp; the god of thy ſede after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>) was for his promiſſes ſake a God, that is a ſauioure vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that had the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of circumciſion, &amp; was a iuge vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that died vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, as to the breakers of his couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and therfore to be caſt out and rooted furth from theyr people: then haue ye wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten agaynſt ſcripture, where ye holde that none can haue any profit of ſacramentes, excepte they vnderſtande them, heare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and haue conſolation ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. I nede not here reherſe the ſtory of the raynbow, which ye cal your ſelf a ſacrament, wher by I proued that euen the byr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:1922:78"/> and vnreaſonable beaſtes had profyt all though they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heard the promiſſ, nor knew that it was a Sacrament: for I haue intreated of that mater largely here before. your argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I truſt, now is confuted &amp; all the falſe doctrine that ye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to byld vpon the ſame. now wyl I let the reder ſe your next argument, and anſwer to it as well as I can.
<q>Chriſte had his diſciples to preach the confortable tydynges to euery creature of mankynde: but he neuer had baptiſe other then ſuch as at theyr preachiryg wold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Chriſt ſayde vnto his diſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples preache the goſpel to euery creature, but he ſayde not prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the goſpell to euery creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of mankynde, as ye do ſay ſin doyng where of ye committ I dolatry, or at the leſte a graet of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb facs="tcp:1922:78"/> agaynſt GOD, after your own iugement your argument: childer ought not to be baptiſed becauſe Chriſt neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded in the ſcripture expreſſedly the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be baptiſed: and ſo becauſe Chriſt ſayd not expreſſedly prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che the goſpell to euery creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynde but ſayd as ſaynt marke writeth. <q rend="inline">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q> that is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the goſpel vnto euery crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ye do wrong to ſay which is not expreſſed in the ſcripture in the ſtede of euery creature of mankynde. If that ye aunſwer to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, euery creature of mankynde, &amp; take vnto yow autorite to vnderſtande y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as ye thynk beſt: why may not I in this text.
<q>
                  <hi>Euntes, docete omnes gentes baptizantes eas.</hi>
               </q> Vnder the name of al nationes
<pb facs="tcp:1922:79"/> vnderſtand yong ſpecheles chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, as ye vnder the name of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery creature vnderſtande eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry creature of man kynde, ſeing that a childe may as wel be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded, vnder the name of nationes, as man kynde may be vnderſtanded vnder the name of al creatures? If that Chriſte bad hys diſciples preache the goſpell vnto euery creature of mankynde, what kynde are yong chylder the creatures of? of horſe, bulles, or hogges, or of mankynd, yf they be creatures of mankynde: then muſt they haue the worde preached vnto them by your interpretation: is not thys interpretation a prety one that it had alſo nede of an other interpretation? Myght ye not as well haue ſayd to all kyndes of men of euery nation
<pb facs="tcp:1922:79"/> that can vnderſtand prechyng? Becauſe ye ſhal not thynk that your argument is ſure &amp; ſtrong where ye reſon that Chriſt bad not hys Apoſtelles by expreſſed wordes baptiſe chyldern: ther for they ought not to baptyſe chylder: I make ſuch lyke nega<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiue argumentes of ſcripture: whych if they be not ſure but fal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe and foliſhe: then ſeyng that of lyke thynges lyke iugement is to begyuen, your negatiue ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>argument is both vnſuer falſe and fooliſhe.</p>
            <p>Chriſte neuer commanded yow, to were a ryng on your fin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, and be cauſe it ſhuld not be ſmothered vnder your gloue, to make a wyndow to let the ayre cum in to it, I dare not ſay that it myght be ſeene, nether co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de he yow to ſyng in his church
<pb facs="tcp:1922:80"/> any pypyng Chriſte neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded pryckſong or any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy diſcant: therfore ye offend to be a curious muſician.</p>
            <p>GOD bad his diſciples ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer expreſſedly in hys ſcripture preach that wymen ſhulde cum to te communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: therfore ought no woman cum to the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>GOD neuer in his worde expreſſedly commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtelles to ſuffer ſuche tal men as you bee to lyue ſyngle: ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore your curate doth wrong to ſuffer yow to lyue ſyngle.</p>
            <p>Chriſte neuer commaunded any Chriſten men to differ the baptym of theyr chyldren vnto the .xiiij. yere of theyr age you do therfore wrong to differ the baptiſyng of chyldren vnto the xiiij. yere of their age.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1922:80"/>
            <p>If theſe be not good argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes made euen after the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me maner of yours, that is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue: then is yours, a nough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty argument to ſay, Chriſte ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bad Baptyſe infantes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſedly: therefore chylderen ought not the baptyſed.</p>
            <p>If they be good argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: then all the concluſiones that I gather, are true, and ſo ar ye a fals man and a perillons heretike.</p>
            <p>When as ye ſay that,
<q>By baptym alone is no ſaluation but by baptyme and preachyng:</q>
            </p>
            <p>I aſke you, whether ye mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne hole baptyme, that is bothe the inwarde, and the outwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de baptym togyter or the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde baptyme a loue.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1922:81"/>
            <p>If ye meane of the inwarde bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tym and outwarde bothe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned together: ye hold an ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hereſi agaynſt the ſcripture, for thus wrytethe the Apoſtell of CHRIST ſaynt Pet. j. Pet. iij. few ſowles that is to wit, eyght, were ſaued in the arke throw the water: to the figure where of, baptyme at this tyme anſwering, doth now lykewyſe ſaue vs. Paul alſo the elect veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of GOD, gyueth vnto the right &amp; holy baptym clengyng, and the hole man, and alſo ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, Epheſ. v. huſbandes loue your wyues as Chriſte hathe loued hys churche and gaue hym ſelf for it, that he myght hallow, and cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge it by the bath of water thorow the word, and Tit. iij. But after that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and loue of GOD oure
<pb facs="tcp:1922:81"/> ſauioure towarde vs appered, not of the workes that ar in the righteouſnes which we did, but accordynge vnto hys mercy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs, throwe the bath of the new byrthe, and the renewyng of the ſprite. Paule alſo graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that baptime is of ſuche ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that the receyuyng of it, is the receyuing and puttynge on of Chriſt: is not Chriſt ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? and doth not baptim bring Chriſt? Paules wordes ar the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. As many of you as are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, haue put Chriſt vpon you Then when as Peter doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſedly gyueth ſaluation vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to baptim, and Paule like wiſe, your erroure is open and ſeene of all that haue any eyes to ſe withal. The perfit baptim hath Chriſt, it hath the holy gooſte likewiſe: for thei that ar right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:1922:82"/> baptiſed haue the holy goſte and Chriſt put vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Is not this baptim able to ſaue alone: wherin is Chriſt with his holy ſpirit? if ye meane by this word baptim, only the outward bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time: I graunte you that by it commeth no ſaluation alone, ye moreouer that, it is no parte of ſaluation: but that it is onely a ſigne &amp; a certification of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. But then ye ſhall in to right popiſtry, for ye fall that of preachyng, and baptyme mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of outward baptime com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſaluation: preachyng is a worke of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in opening of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des word, and the outward bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tim is an outward worke, then if theſe twoo together bring ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation: then workes bryng ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. How far are ye ſyr, now from popiſtry whych call other
<pb facs="tcp:1922:82"/> men papiſtes farther from papi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtry then ye are nere vnto the verite? Chriſt ſayeth Mar. xvi He that beleueth and is bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall be ſaued: but he ſayeth not he that heareth the worde of god &amp; hath only the outward baptime layed vpon hym, ſhall be ſaued: ye haue be like autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of youre woode ſpirite to make new textes of ſcripture, and to bylde thereupon what ye lyſt. Other haue ye none. If preaching &amp; baptim be the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to ſaue and damne the hole worlde by? how proue you that baptime is ordened to damne men wythall? let vs heare one word of ſcripture of you to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue this ſtrange opinion withal. But leaſt any man ſhuld thinke that I reherſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye neuer wrote I will write your awn wordes
<pb facs="tcp:1922:83"/>
               <q>By baptime alone is no ſaluation, but by preachyng baptim, &amp; certaine it is, that God is able to ſaue hys choſen Churche wythout thes meanes: But thys is hys ordynary waye, to ſaue and damne the whole worlde, by namely by offeryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge remyſſion of ſynnes and baptime to all the worlde, that thereby the beleuers maye be abſolued from all conſcience of ſynne, and the diſobedient and vnbele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers bounde ſtyll other to amende or to be damned for he that beleueth not is all redy damned.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The offeryng of remiſſion of ſinnes and of baptim is, not the law, whoſe office is to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, but it is the glad tidinges whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we cal the Goſpel: ye are ſo vnlearned and ſo foolyſhe in your reaſonyng, that ye are vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly vnworthy to be reaſoned wythall, ſo that it hath repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me ofte ſence, that I began to write: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I troubled my ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:1922:83"/> wyth ſuch a bungler. But leſte your bablyng &amp; booſting, ſhuld bringe any ſimple people out of the way, I wyl not diſdayne to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your foliſhnes, &amp; to bewray your abhominable hereſies. Saint Paul vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romanes iij. ſayeth: by the law cummeth the knowlege of ſyn. In the .iiij Capter he ſayeth that the law worketh wrathe, and in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth chapter. I haue not kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen ſinne but throw the law, ſo that it is the office of the law to ſhew ſyn and to condemne the worlde, wherfore ye do againſt al ſcriptur to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlate &amp; remoue the office of the lawe vnto the moſte comfortable offeringe of remiſſion of ſyn, and to the moſt ſure ſeale and ſigne of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, baptim: is the ende or office of offering of remiſſion of ſinne
<pb facs="tcp:1922:84"/> is to ſaue &amp; make bleſſed, for thei are bleſſed ſayde Dauid whoſe ſinnes ar forgiuen. What is the Goſpel or glad tidinges, els but the offering of remiſſion of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? Did not Chriſt commaun- hys diſciples to preache repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce and that the kingdom of heauen was at hande? dyd not the angel bring in the tydinges of peace? was not remiſſion of ſynne offered where peace was offered? What other thyng did the Apoſtels els then offer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſynne vnto theyr au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditores? Chriſte commaunded them to preache the Goſpell, and thys Goſpel or gald tydin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, was remiſſion of ſynnes. How can then the offerynge of the Goſpell whyche was orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſaue the worlde, bee a meane to damne the worlde?
<pb facs="tcp:1922:84"/> How can baptime whyche was ordened to bee an inſtrument of ſalmation: be an inſtrument of damnation? The offeryng of remiſſion of ſynnes is the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge of an holſum medecine: Baptime is, as it were a confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue, vſed to bee gyuen vnto the ſyk after purgations. Who is he, that hath the comon wyt, that wyll ſaye, yf a foolyſhe ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke man refuſe an holſum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, with a confortatiue: and he die for lacke of medicine: that the offerynge of the medicine, wyth the confortatiue was the meanes, whereby thys man came vnto hys deathe? Yet doo ye thys: whyle ye make the offerynge of remyſſyon of ſynnes, to bee the meanes, whereby GOD dampneth and ſaueth all the worlde by.
<pb facs="tcp:1922:85"/> If faith do iuſtifie (as oft times ye graunt wyth open mouthe) then doth infidelite condemne: and it is the meane, where by the worlde is condemned, as Chriſt witneſſeth: he that bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not is condemned already Lo here is condemnation aſſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned vnto vnbeleue: and nother to the offerynge of remiſſion of ſinne, nother of baptime. Then may it eaſely be ſpyed how, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learnedly ye alleged thys text: he that beleueth not, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned already: to proue that the offerynge of remyſſyon of ſynnes and baptime, is meanes bothe vnto ſaluation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: namely when as Chriſte, immediatly before ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed the meanes of ſaluation in theſe wordes. He that wyll be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue and be baptiſed, ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.
<pb facs="tcp:1922:85"/> What wood ſpret taught you this foliſh philoſophy: that one cauſe ſhuld bring lurth two diuerſe and contrary effectes, as ar ſaluation &amp; condemnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? It is a great maruell, to ſe ſuch great arrogantie as ye haue, to be ioyned wyth ſo lytle know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege. But ſo are thei al, that are blaſted with the Anabaptiſtical ſprit, as you be. If that I could haue made no other ſhyft, when ye argued with me that al Tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes and Iewes were withoute origynall ſynne: becauſe they had no water offered vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I might here by youre helpe in this place haue anſwered thus: ye ſay that remiſſion of ſyn and baptim is offered vnto all: then when as baptim is not without water: water is offred vnto al, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by your own grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, all haue
<pb facs="tcp:1922:86"/> originall ſynne: whyche ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied ſtoutly before: becauſe ſum wanted the offeryng of water. To that ye ſay the Goſpel hath no powre vpon infantes, and muche leſſe ſacramentes, &amp; that therfore nother preachyng nor adminiſtration of ſacramentes ar dew to infantes, by the word of god: I meruel what ye mean by hauyng power. If ye meane by hauynge power ouer, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe and to be profitable: your ſayng is twiſe falſe: for both, the word of God belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth vnto in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes: preſently, by the reaſon of the promys whyche is made vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the worde, and it is dew vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt thei come to age, as a chylder landes are dewe vnto him, thoughe he can not inioye them afore he come to age: that the adminiſtration
<pb facs="tcp:1922:86"/> of Sacramentes ar dew vnto chyldren: the Sacrament of cir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cumciſyon, and the rayn bow are witneſſes agaynſt you, and proue yow ar a fals &amp; a ſhameles lyer: therfore who wyll beleue yow hereafter? no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſuch as haue delyte in lyes and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable hereſies.</p>
            <p>Youre concluſion, agreeth as well with your antecede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as thys argument doth: folowe a ſtaff ſtandeth in the corner: ergo a man rinneth: and it is of ſuch a faſſhon made, that I dowt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be more folyſhe vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or more malicious: for it pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth, that I brought in to proue that childer had originall ſynne a bruſhe: when as made mention of a bruſh, not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue that chyldren had origy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſynne, but for a ſimilitude,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:87"/> after this maner. Euen as, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one bryngeth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a bruſhe that is commed home from hys ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, it is a ſigne that his clothes ar duſty ſo, when as water is of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fered vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ar baptiſed, it is a token, that they had nede of ſcouryng and clengyng and ar vncleue. Nether dyd I hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, that water dyd ſcoure the ſowle: but I ſhewed, that the water betokened, that the ſowl of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that were baptiſed, had nede of ſcowryng. Then let all chriſtian, and learned men iuge, how learned and charitable is this your concluſion.
<q>So that your bruſhe proueth the conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of infantes, as ruyche as your water: and helpeth alyke to ſcoure the ſame.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ After this your vnlearned and malitious concluſion, ye be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gin
<pb facs="tcp:1922:87"/> a new mater, &amp; feyn a ſayng of your own braine, as thoughe I had ſproken it, and them ye ſcourge me for your fooliſhe, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſhe and vnlearned lyinge: for after theſe my wordes.</p>
            <p>Well it is good to remede a diſeas in the beghinnyng, and to ſtay hys courſe: leſt at lenght it grow ford far, that it be paſt remedie or help.
<q>It is ſpoken lyke a Phiſition: and that maketh yow, to lay a playſter of colde water to the ſynn of infantes, ſo tymely: But ſuerly out of dew tyme, and other to parly or to late, for they ar wors after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Is not thys a prety faſhion of confutyng: for lack of ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, reaſon and learning, to feyn, lye and ſcof, after thys maner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye ar, lyke to wyn but a few ſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lares,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:88"/> that ar honeſt men, after this maner. All myghty God, in the olde Teſtament, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge that the infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wer ſike in original ſyn, gaue them the medicine of remiſſyon of ſynnes: comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that they ſhulde haue circumciſion layde vpon them, as a ſeale, and token of goddis promiſed and fauour vnto them.</p>
            <p>That all myghty GOD promiſed the chylderen of the Iewes remiſſion of ſinnes, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe wordes do teſtifi Geneſ. xvij. I wyll ſtreynge then my cum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nant betwene me, and the, and betwene they ſede after the, in theyr generationes, with an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nant: that I may be a GOD vnto the, and to thy ſede. Then to bee a God is to be a ſauiour: but he ſayde he
<pb facs="tcp:1922:88"/> wolde be a GOD vnto the chyldren of the Iewes: therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re he promyſed that he wold be a ſauiour vnto them. So that the promyſs of ſaluation belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth as well vnto the chyldren, as it perteyneth vnto theyr fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. It is expreſſedly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the ſame chapter, that the loue of GOD was ſo great vnto chylderen, that he not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vnto chylderen ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: but alſo the ſeale and ſygne of ſaluation the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of circumciſion: as the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe wordes bear witnes. Thys is my comnant whych ye ſhall kepe, betwene yow and me, and alſo betwen thy ſede after the: let euery male be circumcyſed among yow.</p>
            <p>But ye ſhal circuncyſe the fleſhe of your forſkynne whiche
<pb facs="tcp:1922:89"/> ſhall be the ſygne of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant betwene yow and me, and they ought to be circuncyſed: that my couenant myght be in your fleſhe.</p>
            <p>If GOD be true (as he can not befalſ) there the yong chylderen obteyned it, That GOD promiſed: and that was remiſſyone of ſynnes, whych was the promiſed bliſſyng, and that GOD commandeth the ſygne and ſeale of remiſſion of ſynne to be layd vpon chyldern, this is alſo certayn. Then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ay all myghty GOD the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chephiſiccon, and heler of both body and ſoule began, ſo tyme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and erly to heale yong chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern: no godly man wyll mock Chriſtes miniſtres, while they lay vpon the infantes of the chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtianes the ſygne of ſaluation,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:89"/> of remiſſion of ſinnes, after that almyghty God hath heled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from originall ſyn as well as he heled the childer of the Iſraeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. If that ye deny that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Iſraelites were hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ye muſt deny that God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed to be a God, vnto them. If they were healed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ar our children alſo healed by theſame phyſician, as erly and tymely as the Iewes chyldren were hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſeyng God loueth the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianes chyldren as well as he dyd the Iewes chyldren, and hys promis of helth and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion was as well made vnto our children, as to the Iewes chylder. All chylder ar infected with originall ſynne, whiche if it were not taken away, ſhould turne them to damnacion: then to offer vp chylder vnto Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:90"/> that they may receyue at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>templacion of the prayers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, and for the promis that God made vnto them, remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theyr originall vnclenenes, is that to tymely don when as they ar conceyued in wykked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and borne in ſynne? But I know your meanyng well. ye ar of that mynde that ye thynke that chylder haue no ſynne, and that therfore ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that they nether nede god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis phyſik, nor any ſeale of hys promis, whiche mygh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> comfort them when they cum to age. And for thys cauſe it is lyke that ye wyll haue none bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized vntyll they be of four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene yeares of age, that then your brether poyſoned, wyth many a damnable ſynne, might be heled by baptyme and by
<pb facs="tcp:1922:90"/> preachyng as thoughe before that tyme, that they neded no Phyſik of GOD our princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Phiſician. Chylder of one daye haue nede of the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician Chriſte or no: If they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de none of Chriſte, he dyed not for them. If they nede Chriſte the Phyſiciane, when as they be but one daye olde: It is not to erly nor to tymely to cary the chylder by the prayers of the churche vnto Chryſte, that he may hele them. And when as the offerers vp of the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, truſtyng vnto the promys of GOD, that the chylder ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue granted vnto them remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theyr originall ſynne, do lay vpon them the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of bapti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, do they any otherwiſe vnto their childer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes
<pb facs="tcp:1922:91"/> ſumtyme the people of God, did vnto theyr chylder after the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of God: Then we nede not greatly care for your vnlearned, and hetheniſh moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Chriſtes holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, callyng it in mockage a playſter of colde water. Who dyd orden this cold water? dyd not Chriſt orden it? If ye be a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and not a Lucia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, why do ye mok it? ſhall y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> excuſe you when ye ſhall ſaye that I gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that it is Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis plaſter, but that it is to ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely layde to? ought Chriſtis ſacrament to be mocked &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghed to ſcorn, becauſe a foole layeth it to, out of tyme? Take hede what ye do, for Iuliane y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtata, as proud a mocker as you be, payed derely for hys mockyng whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he caſt his blode in to the ayer, and ſayde vnto
<pb facs="tcp:1922:91"/> Chriſt <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>uiciſti Galilaee</hi>
               </q> thou haſt won thow man of Galile. If that an Hethen man ſhould haue ſayd vnto a prieſt of moſis law whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he circunciſed a chylde: what ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ye ſyr ſurgean, to cut thys chyld before he be ſik. I befoole ſuch ſurgeanes, as leue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der worſe then they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d them: thynke ye that GOD would not puniſhe this prophane moc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker? ye ſuerly: then thynk you to ſcape fre, whiche would: be rekened a chriſten man, and yit mok baptim the ordinaunce of Chriſte? I think no. And where as ye ſay that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylder ar wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, after their baptim then euer they were before: it appereth that ye mene that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrament of baptim is an euel thyng. for if ye ment that it were not euell, why ſhulde ye ſay that chylder
<pb facs="tcp:1922:92"/> baptized ar worſe after theyr baptim then they were before? After thys your Poeticall fey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ye bring in a clerkly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion whiche ye bylde vpon your own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication, &amp; therwith a reſon as wytty, and wiſe as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former was, and as wel it agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with it that goeth before. giue eare vnto this new orator
<q>For I heare of a poke that is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng to ſpryng vp, not of a romyſh pok, but of an other deuelyſh pok, as euell as it. <hi>Medice cura te ipſum.</hi> The deuelyſh pok whiche is ſyn is not healed but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row faythe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſyr I pray yow tell me by your rhetorik &amp; logike how foloweth this ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> goeth before? for me think it foloweth not. <q rend="inline">It is ſpoken lyke a phiſicion &amp; that maketh yow to ley a plaſter of colde wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the ſynne of the infantes ſo tymely, but ſuerly out of dew tyme, and other to
<pb facs="tcp:1922:92"/> yearly or to late, for they ar worſe after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward then euer th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y were before. For I heare of of a pok that is now begynnyng to ſpryng vp. &amp;ce.</q> This gear is ſcarſe clerkly cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched together, and yit ye wil be rekened a great clerke. But I wyll pas ouer your art whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I can not fynde in yow, and I wyll try your ſentences, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther they be any better then your compoſitiones ar or no. ye ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye heare of a pok, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is now beginni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to ſpring vp, &amp; ye ſay immediatly afterward y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the poke ye meane of is ſin. That is in begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning to ſpring, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer before: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yn be now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to ſpring, as your wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ſuppoſe it to do, it is lyke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ar of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> before this ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me there was neuer any ſyn. If this do not folow of your ſaye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g:
<pb facs="tcp:1922:93"/> I am far deceyued &amp; appele vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudgement of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which haue but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſence, whether this foloweth of your ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or no</p>
            <p>Where as ye ſay, <hi>medice curate ipſum,</hi> that is to ſay Phiſicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le thy ſelfe, ye reken ye haue don a clerkly worck in ſpeakyng ſo mych latin vnengliſſhed, and in applying of a prouerbe ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly. But how litle it pertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto thys preſent purpoſe euery wiſe man may eaſely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue. As for me although I am a Phyſician, called to hele mennis bodies, whiche thyng by the help of my Lorde God, I haue oft do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, I neuer preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be an heler of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nis ſoul w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my phiſik but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chrſtis phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſik. &amp; although it pleaſeth ſumti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes almighty god to hele diuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe dedly ſiknes in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſoules by
<pb facs="tcp:1922:93"/> me &amp; ſuche like and to call them vnto fayth, to true repentance, and ſo conſequently to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> health of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule, yit do we not take our ſelues to be Phyſicianes &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the ſoules, but onely the chefe phyſicians ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, &amp; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giuyners vnto the ſik ſoules ſuche medicines as our maſter hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded vs, not beyng ſo bolde as to deuyſe any Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſik at all of our own braynes. Then to ſay vnto me, Phyſicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heale thy ſelfe is as much to ſay as thou which art a phiſicion of the body, go and playe Goddis parte and hele thy own ſowle. Thys is the counſell, not of the ſpirite of God: but of the wood ſprete, who taught yow yowr diuinite. If that ye had bene well aduiſed, ye wolde not haue made your ſelf a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:1922:94"/> murderi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſcribes, &amp; phariſes, in vſing their churliſh cheke agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt one of Chriſtis me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres: whiche they threw out agaynſt Chriſte him ſelf. But what win you by your chek? haue ye proued any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g therby? nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at al ſaui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men may know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ar wel ſene in doggiſhe eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Ye haue, ſence y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of your book vnto this place, ſaid more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iij times, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faith alone taketh awai ſinnes in whiche places ye haue erred ſhamefully, if ye mean by only fayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only work of bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. For if y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye giue iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> work, of beleui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g not mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſay faith iuſtifieth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercy of god promiſed vnto vs, by Chriſtis blood iuſtifieth vs, &amp; haue a reſpect only vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dede of beleui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: ye ar a iuſticiari w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old phariſes: who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe
<pb facs="tcp:1922:94"/> prouerbes ye gladly exerciſe. If that ye mean by this ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce: faith iuſtifieth: that fayth ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hold of the mercy of God, whych is granted vnto vs by Chriſtes blood: then dothe the mercy of God iuſtifi, &amp; take ſyn away: &amp; fayth doth nothyngel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis but taketh hold of the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; offered mercy. Then, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the mercy of God is as well promiſed vnto chylderen as to old folk: childer mai be aswel be ſaued thereby, as old folk: &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue theyr vnclenenes as well ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away by it, as old folk haue theyr offences taken away by it, allthoughe they be not as yit cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med vnto the vſe of faythe. I bryng for an example the infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the Iewes, whoſe natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall vnclenenes other God, tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>row his mercy, took away befor
<pb facs="tcp:1922:95"/> they cam vnto the vſe of fayth: or elles they were all damned, for they were both gotten and born in original ſyn. Then your general propoſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not trew, without a trew vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding &amp; nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt me, nother ſerueth it for your purpoſe with a trew vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding: for ye bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g it into proue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chylder haue no ſyn: &amp; thus wold ye haue reſoned, and ye had had learnynge to your mynde. Where as there is no faith, there is no remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: but no chylde hath faythe: therfore no chyld hath remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynnes. If that chylder had ſynnes, they ſhuld haue had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of them by faythe: but when as they haue no faythe: then haue they nether ſynne, nor remiſſion of ſynne, I haue twiſe al redy a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwered vnto this
<pb facs="tcp:1922:95"/> your argument before: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall not nede at thys ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to confite it any more.</p>
            <p>Where as ye thynk, that I am not healed from ſynne my ſelf becauſe I wold haue yong chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> baptiſed: I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not let yow to thynk of me, what ye liſt: but if ye iuge falſly, there is a iuge wil poniſhe yow for your falſ iuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And to ſay that I am not heled from the romiſſhe pok, is ſuche a lyke wepo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as .ij. wyues ſcoldyng vpon .ij. dong hylles te vſe to feygh whyh, one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt an other. The on ſayeth thow art a drab: the other aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, why ſhe is a drab: the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer anſwereth, for thow art a drab, ſhewyng no cauſe why y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hyr neybor ſhuld be a drab, Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ye haue ſayd ſence the begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng of your bok diuerſ tymes,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:96"/> that the baptym of chylder is a popiſh ordinance, &amp; here ye ſaye that the romiſhe pok is to bapti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe infantes: but ye haue not as yit ſhewed one worde, to proue that, the baptyme of chylderen was popiſhe: except that your oft reherſall of it be a ſufficient profe, to proue it with all, thynk you: becauſe ye haue with your importune bablyng bewiched certayn vnlnearned ſimple me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that thei beleue to be true what ſoeuer ye ſay ons vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that your thryſe ſayng of a lye ſhall purches credence, becauſe ye do ſo oft repete the ſame: Can it that is by nature falſe, by oft re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>herſyng, be cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true: what other profe haue ye hither to brought that the baptym of chylder is popiſhe, ſayng only your own oft reherſal of it: whych hath as
<pb facs="tcp:1922:96"/> mych autoryte with me, and all that cleue to the wryten worde of GOD, as the goſpell of Munſter hathe.</p>
            <p>Hytherto haue ye bene about to confute my opinion, that yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g chyldren may be baptyſed: but ye haue brought in for you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge, ſauyng one text of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, and that negatiue: Which I truſte, I haue ſo taken from you, that it dyd not ſerue your purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Now doth my opynion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde ſtyll vnmoued: and vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued: and yit haue ye donn that ye can: ye may ſe what it awayleth your wood ſprete to fyght agaynſt the ſcripture.</p>
            <p>Then ye, beyng wery in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng in this mater, with ſmall honeſtie begyn a newe mater: that is, that chylderen haue no
<pb facs="tcp:1922:97"/> originall ſynne: and in the fyrſt ſayeng, ye ar as clere agaynſte your ſelf afterwarde, as here is to colde, &amp; lyght vnto darknes: for thus do ye begyn.
<q>But your deueliſhe pok is thys to cleare infantes from ſynn whiche ye call origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</q>
            </p>
            <p>¶ If thys he a deueliſhe pok: then haue ye the deuelles pok for ye go erneſtly about to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, that chyldern haue no origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſynne. And as for me it is as manifeſte as the clere daye lyght, that I do not clere chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from originall ſynn: for that is one of the maters that I go moſte earneſtly about in my ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon, to proue that chylder ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue originall ſynn: not wichſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, that I do grant, that all myghty GOD purgeth and
<pb facs="tcp:1922:97"/> ſcoureth them from it in theyr infancie, by his mercy, accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vnto his promyſe, which he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vnto them. By this contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, with it that foloweth here after, ye may bether learne this great clerk is wit, and the agrement of his ſpirite with it ſelf. Then after this monſtrous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ye bruſt into a ſterk<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye, which is conteyned in theſe wordes folowyng.
<q>¶ This is the pok ye take in hande to cure, ether with water or fyer.</q> I neuer went about to take ori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginal ſyn away by water: but I went about to proue, that chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der had original ſinne, and that Chriſte taketh the ſame ſynne from chylder, by his promyſed mercy: and that therfore the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of baptim ſhuld be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto them, as a ſygne, and
<pb facs="tcp:1922:98"/> ſeale of ſaluation, whiche they haue receyued by the merites of Chriſtis paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It is therfore both maliciouſly, &amp; lyingly ſayd of yow, that I take in hande to cure originall ſyn with water. And of lyke truthe is it that ye wryte in the margen, that I go about to cure yow with fyre. For if I wolde haue gon about that: I knew and know mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes enow to bryng that to pas. For as muche as ye ar an open felon againſt the kyngis lawes, and haue committed ſuche felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as ye ar excepted out of the pardon, where of theues and robbers ar partakers. Almy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghty GOD amende yow, and bryng yow in to the hygh way agayn, and ſaue yow from it, that ye haue iuſtly deſerued.</p>
            <p>The firſt argument that ye
<pb facs="tcp:1922:98"/> make to proue, that chylder ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue no originall ſynne, is this.
<q>¶ If Chriſte had counted infantes ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with Adames ſinne, as ye do: he wold neuer haue ſent his Apoſtelles &amp; vs vnto childer to be defyled of them. But now he ſendeth vs thyther for clennes, to becum ſuche as they ar, if we wold entre into the kyngdom of God: waſſhed to the vnwaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, Chriſtened to the vnchriſtened, bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers to vnbeleuers. Not to becum pocky or leproſe, but that we ſhuld be ful of inno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie &amp; ſimplicite. For it is write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: except ye conuert &amp; becum as theſe infantes ye ſhall not entre in to the kyngdom of heuenes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I am glad that ye ar now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, to allege ſcripture for your purpoſe. Hetherto ye haue fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghten agaynſt me only with, I ſay, and certayn ſcoldynges, &amp; vnreaſonable reſones which ye feyned of your own brayne.</p>
            <p>But now let vs ſe how ryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ye haue alleged the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:1922:99"/> and whether, it that ye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende, doth folow of the place alleged or no.</p>
            <p>Chriſt ſeyng the diſputacion of the hartes of his diſciples amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them ſelues, who ſhuld be grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt among them, as Matthew and Luke do teſtify: ſet a chyld amongeſt them and ſeyde: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that ye be turned, and be made lyke vnto litle chylder, ye ſhall neuer entre in to the kyng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom of heuen. Chriſte byddeth hys diſciples here to learne of chylder humilite, and to flye am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bition, where with he ſaw them entangled. Chriſte byddeth not vs learne al vertues of childer, but onely hmmilite, and fliyng of ambition. Now I pray yow how folowe theſe argumentes chylder ar not deſierous of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor: ergo they haue no original
<pb facs="tcp:1922:99"/> ſynne, Chriſt ſendeth vs to lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne humilite of childer: ergo thei are not defyled with the ſynne of Adame. If theſe be good ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ar alſo they that folow good argumentes.</p>
            <p>Peter was no thiefe: ergo Peter was no fyghter. Mary magdaleyn was no murderer: therfore ſhe was no vnclene wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man of her body. If theſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes do not folow: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth not thys your argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t folow. childer ar not proud &amp; deſirous of honor: therefore they ar not defyled with originall ſynne. &amp; becauſe your argument ſemeth to lene vpon this pyller: Chriſte ſendeth his Apoſtelles and vs to learne of none that is defy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, with any ſynne: I wyll exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min it, &amp; (I truſt) ouerthrow it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> examples of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture.
<pb facs="tcp:1922:100"/> Chriſte in the is of Luke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth vs to folow the wyk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſtewarde, and bryngeth hym for an example to be folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed in wyſdome. Was thys wykked ſtewarde with out ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſynne, and vndefyled by Adame, becauſe Chriſt ſendeth vs vnto hym, to learne wiſdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in one point? Chriſt ſendeth vs alſo vnto ſerpentes to lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne wiſdome: be ye wyſe ſayeth he, as ſerpentes, and ſymple as doues. Haue ſerpentes no poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe Chriſte ſendeth vs vnto them, to learne wiſdome? Paule exhorteth them that he writeth vnto, to folow hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: was Paule without ſyn, becauſe he exhorted hys Diſciples to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low hym? No. for he graunteth in diuerſe places in the Epiſtel to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romanes both generally &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:1922:100"/> particularely, that he is a ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: and yet not withſtandynge he exhorteth his diſciples to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low hym ſayng: be you the folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of me, as I folow Chriſt. So maye we folowe childer as they folowe Chriſte in humilite and lowlines, and yet their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milite doth not, proue they are cleare fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> original <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynne. What if I graunted you, that the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that Chriſt ſet furth for vs to folowe, where at that tyme clere from origynall ſynne, as I recken they wer in dede (for it is lyke they were chylder of the Iewes, and hadde the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys, and hadde receyued the ſeale of the promys: cyrcum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſyon, and therefore was clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from theyr originall ſynne that it ſhulde not bee imputed vnto them) ſhall it folowe,
<pb facs="tcp:1922:101"/> that they had no original ſynne before? No. For God purgeth chylder as well as men from originall ſyn. Therfore thys text of ſcripture, whiche ye ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue alleged out of Mathew, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth nothyng, that childer ar fre from originall ſynne and ſo, where as ye thought that by the ſtrengthe of your inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, it ſhuld haue bene eaſy to haue aunſwered to my argumentes made, to proue that chylder were borne in ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſynne, your wepon taken from yow, it is as harde to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute my argumentes as it was before.</p>
            <p>Diuerſe other abſurdites &amp; inconueniences folow vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your fooliſh aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſayeng namely this. <q rend="inline">Chriſte, ſay ye, the prynce of phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiciones, ſendeth, his chefe ſurgeones and
<pb facs="tcp:1922:101"/> phyſiciones to be cum ſuche as the babes wer,</q> but ye ſay a litle after that <q rend="inline">y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childer were vnwaſſhed, vnchriſtened, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leuers.</q> Then ſent Chriſte hys a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtels, by your ſayng, to yong chylder, to learne of them to be vnwaſhed, vnchriſtened &amp; to be faythles. Ye ſet in your marge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ouer agaynſt thys your argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with many other wordes <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>uirgines enim ſunt. &amp; dealbauerunt ueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta ſua in ſanguine agui.</hi> For they are pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re virgines and they haue made whyte their garmentes in the blood of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lambe.</q> If that this text perteyn vnto chylder, as yow do allege it, ye haue brought me .ij. ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tines to ſhoote againſt yow. with the firſt I wil ouerthrow your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that chylder ar not borne in originall ſynne: and wyth the ſecund your falſe lye, where as ye ſayd that chylder were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waſſhed. If that chylder had
<pb facs="tcp:1922:102"/> their garmentes made whyte, then was their garmentes once not white: then if whitnes beto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keneth clennes, &amp; other colores vncle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes: it foloweth that they were once vnclene, for all that they wer afterward come vnto ſuch whitnes &amp; clenenes, by the blood of the lambe. If that thei made white their clothes in the blood of the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, then wer they wel waſſhed. Who can be better waſſhed then thei be, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with Chriſtes blood? then are the childer waſſhed, and ye ſklander the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vnclennes, &amp; yf thei be waſſhed, then were they before vnclene: but they had no other vncle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſauyng original ſyn: thefore by this text of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur childer haue had original ſin &amp; by the blood of the lambe are ſcoured &amp; purged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſame.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1922:102"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>MEruell not good reader that I haue not anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto the reſt of thys ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s boke: for I wold as gladly haue anſwered vnto the reſt as to it whiche I anſwered to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but that I haue ſo muche ado wyth the ſettyng out of my Herball, that I can not do that at thys tyme. But here after God wyllynge I ſhall make an ende of it, that I haue begon, yf it ſhall be thought expedient to the churche to do ſo. Almighty God kepe the from al phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall and ſtraunge ſpretes and their learnyng. alſo. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb facs="tcp:1922:103"/>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Randol Hurlſt vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the Reader.</head>
               <l>If that the Scottes, or foren folke our contrey ſhoulde aſſayle,</l>
               <l>Wyth courage, ferce, and weapons ſtrong, from vs it for to take,</l>
               <l>A man myght fynde ynow, that wolde not haue them to preuayle,</l>
               <l>But would moſte ſtoutly ſtryue, and ſtande, their fercenes for to ſlake.</l>
               <l>And yet almoſte there none is founde, that in a greater wyght,</l>
               <l>Wyll take in hande the fayth of Chriſte, from ſuche for to defend,</l>
               <l>As teache falſe doctrine euery where, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth wolde vs freyght,</l>
               <l>Denieng Baptyme to oure Babes, and what ſo it dothe ſende.</l>
               <l>Whoſe doctrine, ſuche as Godly are do know, is very naught,</l>
               <l>And that it is more poyſonfull, and hurteth farre more ſore,</l>
               <l>Then yf oure contreyſhold from vs, by force be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer caught,</l>
               <l>And we in thraldom ſhould be the throne, to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue for euer more.</l>
               <l>Wherewith thys author beyng moued, toke pen in hand to wryte,</l>
               <l>Agaynſt all fuche, as the, and thyue of treuth wolde haue bereſt:</l>
               <l>Whome thanke dere reader for hys payne, that he thus wolde endite,</l>
               <l>For the defence, of the and thyne, in that that Chriſte hath leſt.</l>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
               <head>THOMAS SOMVS ECCLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiastes Lectori.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Myſtica baptiſmi, libris quae clauſa teguntur</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:1922:103"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nuncia nonnullis, hic manifeſta patent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Huc igitur ſtudioſa cohors properare iuuabit</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caelica ſi uerba &amp; dogmata ſacra placent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quam dabit hic claui hac reſerabis clauſtra daturam</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quae tenet area intus conſpicienda palam.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Impiger, ut nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mos cumulet, mercator ad Indos</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Currit, at incertertae pendet ab ore Deae:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Huc properes &amp; tutus eris, ſapientia ditat</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fortuna nunquam deficiente ſuos.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
               <head>THOMAS BECONVS Eccleſiaſtes Lectori.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quando ita diuini fert immutanda uoluntas</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Numinis, aſsiduo cunctorum marte ſuorum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Explorare fidem, constantia pectora, morum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Inuictum robur: confirmaturus in illis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hac ratione ſui, ſimul &amp; pietatis amorem:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Implorari ſui docturus corde fideli</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spiritus auxilium: nos quorum cura ſuorum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Commiſſa eſt fidei, uigiles<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> duces<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tuendis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Praeficimur castris, te nunc tibi quanta mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Immineant, miles Christi, diſcrimina uitam</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si ſapis &amp; ſaluam cupis in ſtatione manere</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tuta praecipimus, ſummo uitare maligni</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:1922:104" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Inſidias hostis ſtudio, fraudem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cauere,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sed ne tela tibi deſint, quêis fortiter illi</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Occurras, uires diuino robore frangas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et quae parta ſuo precioſo ſanguine Chriſtus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tradidit, &amp; partam bello tueare quietem:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Scripturae armabit te plena panoplia ſacrae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ex qua cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> malo liceat depromere quicquid</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Seruiat arcendo. Quod ſi liuore maligno</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Commotus pueris baptiſmi munera paruis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Extorquere uelit, iam partae ſigna ſalutis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tibi curare tuam ſolatia prolem</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeternum reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dominum patrem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> bonorum:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ecce parata adſunt tibi munimenta tuis<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et tela inuictis fundentia uiribus hostem,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Turneri hoc opera factum, cui ſaepe Papiſtae</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Inſignem uicti palmam, laudem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> dedere,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cui Deus aeternam tranſactae praemia uitae</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Donabit uitam: Tu grates pectore grato</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tantis pro meritis age gratus, te<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tuere</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fortiter atque tuos, &amp; uires frange malorum.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Militiae tandem finis continget, ouans<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cum Chriſto duce tum caelum tua uota ſubibis.</hi>
               </l>
               <trailer>Vale,</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:1922:104"/>
               <head>Robert Thomlynſon to the reder.</head>
               <l>As wede deſtroyd the corne, and made it oft decaye:</l>
               <l>And dredfull damp dokill the fiſh, that in the water play:</l>
               <l>And the ſerpents in the graſſe oft tymes men do greue,</l>
               <l>That think on them none ill, but very well beleue:</l>
               <l>So haue theſe Catabaptiſtes a very long ſpace</l>
               <l>Encombred Gods word, in many aſundry place,</l>
               <l>Till a Phyſician by Gods myght and power</l>
               <l>With triacle of Gods word that poyſon doth ſcower.</l>
               <l>Wherfor praiſe we God, that ſitteth on hye,</l>
               <l>Which for ſuch ſores ſuch ſalues neuer dothe denye.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London, for Androw Heſter dwellyng in Powles Churchyarde, at the wytt horſſe next to Powles ſcole. An. 1551. the 30 of Ianuarij.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum Priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
